<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="/home/twfy-live/parldata/scrapedxml/lordspages/daylord2021-12-10a.xml" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2105.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2105.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2105.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2105.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2105.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2105.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2110.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2110.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2112.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2112.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2113.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2113.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2115.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2115.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2117.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2117.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2117.0" speakername="Baroness Stowell of Beeston" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25032" colnum="2117" time="10:57:00" url="">
    <p pid="a2117.0/1">My Lords, it is a great privilege to take part in the most reverend Primate’s annual debate. I think it is the first time I have done so since becoming a Member of your Lordships’ House. In responding to his Motion, I will take a perhaps more practical approach than many others speaking today.</p>
    <p pid="a2117.0/2">I should start by being absolutely clear that freedom of speech is critical to a healthy society and democracy. Institutions across all sectors must allow all of us to exercise that fundamental right. However, I would be concerned if we felt it necessary to make this a primary purpose for organisations which exist to serve everyone—especially in an age which feels increasingly intolerant and hostile when people disagree. Let me try to explain why.</p>
    <p pid="a2117.0/3">I start by stating the obvious. Our institutions play a vital role in society. Many are the glue which unites us, so we need them to keep pace with and stay relevant in a modern world. If they have been established for the benefit of everyone more broadly, they need to retain the tacit support of everyone. Those responsible for running these institutions must be respectful of other people’s points of view. To be clear, I mean views which may be different to their personal opinions. That sounds obvious, but too often in practice institutional leaders are not doing it as well or as consistently as they need to. That is often why too many of our very important institutions get embroiled in controversies and why some of them are in jeopardy. Indeed, it is why some people feel that they are contributing to society’s divisions instead of helping us bridge our divides.</p>
    <p pid="a2117.0/4">For me, our starting point should be demanding that our institutions, which exist to serve everyone, deliver their central purpose in a way that shows they understand and respect the expectations of everyone. In simple terms, that means being open and accountable, taking every legitimate complaint seriously and taking every complainant seriously. These are reasonable expectations in exchange for the support they rely on from taxpayers, customers or consumers, many of  whom will have different views or a different perspective on a whole range of things to those who run these institutions. Their difference does not delegitimise them. Indeed, many people whose support institutions rely on will not even have definitive opinions, ready for instant expression, about the root causes of inequality, how best to tell the story of Britain, or even on the exercise and limits of free speech. They just want what they are paying for to meet the standards that they expect and for some of our most important institutions to be an antidote to politics and division, not another front on which to wage a war against political enemies.</p>
    <p pid="a2117.0/5">I know that those same institutions will say that their dilemma is how to serve everyone in this increasingly complex and fractured world without taking sides, and how to stay relevant and meet the demands of a forever-changing, modern world. The short answer is that there is no easy or quick answer, which is why, understandably, they often find it hard to resist when a new movement or campaign comes along with what seems like a short cut to modernity or easy access to an underserved section of the population that they have a duty to serve. However, any cause that promotes a position as if it is accepted wisdom and what all right-minded people think when contested needs to be treated with huge caution. When you exist for everyone’s benefit, you cannot jeopardise the support of your old friends in favour of some new ones. You need to think carefully and move slowly.</p>
    <p pid="a2117.0/6">Our independent institutions, which are so important, need to understand that politics is not just partisan. In fact, they do not get to decide what constitutes “political” in the eyes of the public. Those who object to what they see as the politicisation of institutions are not, as is often alleged, themselves committing a political act. Their concerns need to be taken seriously by the people responsible for those institutions, not just those at the extreme of either side of a political divide or a contentious debate.</p>
    <p pid="a2117.0/7">It is possible to modernise and bring everyone with you. I am proud to say that the House of Lords demonstrated that when we debated and passed the equal marriage legislation eight years ago. The critical thing we did, which was different to the way in which MPs operated in the House of Commons, was remove the politics and show respect for people who were uncertain about what was proposed. In return for that respect, we were given a hearing to make the case for something new, big and bold. That led to bigger majorities here than in the other place, so we have shown that it is possible to do these things and bring people with us.</p>
    <p pid="a2117.0/8">I am grateful to the most reverend Primate for securing today’s debate; as I said, it is a real privilege to take part in it. In my view, the best way for our institutions to uphold the principle of free speech is to respect and keep pace with modern public expectations in fulfilling their fundamental purpose and to stay out of all politics.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2118.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2118.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2120.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2120.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2121.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2121.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2123.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2123.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2124.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2124.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2126.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2126.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2128.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2128.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2129.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2129.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2131.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2131.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2132.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2132.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2133.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2133.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2135.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2135.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2137.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2137.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2139.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2139.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2141.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2141.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2142.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2142.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2145.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2145.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2146.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2146.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2148.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2148.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2149.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2149.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2152.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2152.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2153.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2153.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2155.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2155.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2157.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2157.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2159.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2159.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10a.2164.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2021-12-10b.2164.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

