<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="/home/twfy-live/parldata/scrapedxml/lordspages/daylord2018-03-21b.xml" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.257.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.257.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.257.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.257.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.257.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.257.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.257.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="257" time="11:06:00" url="">
    <p pid="b257.2/1">Amendment 242A</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.257.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.257.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.257.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.257.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.259.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.259.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.259.0" speakername="Lord Wallace of Tankerness" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13940" colnum="259" time="11:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b259.0/1">My Lords,  I support the amendment moved by the noble  Lord, Lord Low of Dalston, and also support Amendment 245A, to which he also spoke. He has given a very comprehensive explanation as to the origins of the amendments and why we believe that they are important.</p>
    <p pid="b259.0/2">Two weeks ago, when we were debating Amendment 70A and other related amendments, one suggested that there should not be any change to equalities legislation, and the noble Lord, Lord Callanan, in responding indicated that that might not be appropriate. He said:</p>
    <p pid="b259.0/3">“For example, the Equality Act refers in several places to EU or to Community law. These references are likely to need to be replaced with the term, ‘retained EU law’. As such, we believe that it is essential that the Clause 7 power is able to address these deficiencies so that we can ensure that the legislation that safeguards these rights and protections can continue to function effectively”.—[Official Report, 7/3/2018; col. 1168.]</p>
    <p pid="b259.0/4">The amendment gets around the practical objection that the noble Lord, Lord Callanan, had to previous ones because, if all that was being done was changing  terminology from EU law to EU retained law, clearly the test or certification referred to in Amendment 245A that the regulation did not,</p>
    <p pid="b259.0/5" class="indent">“remove or diminish any protection provided by or under equalities legislation”,</p>
    <p pid="b259.0/6">would be quite easily met.</p>
    <p pid="b259.0/7">The noble Lord, Lord Low, indicated some of the background to this amendment. An amendment was brought forward in the House of Commons in response to concerns expressed by the Women and Equalities Select Committee. He also indicated that what the Government did in their response really did little more than to reiterate a public sector equality duty that was already there under the Equalities Act. One reason why we were concerned that that was an inadequate response was, as the Minister responding to this will be well aware, that the public sector equality duty goes much further than just the one that has been put in this Bill. Given that in bringing forward secondary legislation, Schedule 19 of the Equality Act 2010 indicates that the public sector equalities duty is on Ministers when bringing forward subordinate legislation, on the principle of inclusio unius exclusio alterius—</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.260.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.260.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.260.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.260.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.261.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.261.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.262.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.262.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.262.0" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13512" colnum="262" time="11:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b262.0/1">My Lords, I will speak to Amendment 246 in this group—entre nous, I support the amendments from the noble Lord, Lord Low; they are rather good, and I can well understand why colleagues have added their voices in support. My amendment picks up a slightly different point. It emanates from the excellent report from the Constitution Committee, which in its summary, at paragraph 33, recommended that the Government bring forward statements accompanying regulations which modify retained EU law so that they provide an explanation of the intention of the modification to guide the courts.</p>
    <p pid="b262.0/2">One of the endearing frustrations of this House, and no doubt the other place, is that we can have very little purchase on statutory instruments. Rightly, I think, they are unamendable, but clearly there has to be a way of improving the understanding of what a statutory instrument does. This legislation is riddled with Henry VIII powers and powers that I think go well beyond what a Minister should properly have access to in making, effectively, law by decree. That is the central concern of a lot of the recommendations in the Constitution Committee’s report. We are asking  here for the Minister to ensure that, when a statutory instrument is brought forward, it has to satisfy a test of appropriateness under the relevant sections, state an intention of any proposed modification from the retained EU law that is carried over and provide guidance to courts to assist with interpretation.</p>
    <p pid="b262.0/3">Reflecting back on some of the more recent debates on statutory instruments in your Lordships’ House—for instance, last night’s debate on free school meals—I wonder whether it would be helpful to your Lordships if we had a better understanding and explanation of those statutory instruments. The thing that always comes across to me when I listen to debates on SIs is this: there is very poor background information. The statistical data that is supposedly there to underpin the argument is often missing; the impact assessments have not been done; and we do not really understand the real effect of what is before us. In my book, that means that there is a lot of scope for the Government to get away with things. I do not think that is right or a product of good lawmaking.</p>
    <p pid="b262.0/4">I want to hear the Minister say that the Government will take the issue seriously. that they will consider bringing forward amendments to satisfy these points, because they need to be satisfied and the House will want to hear them being satisfied, and that in the future we will get clear statements of intent when there is a change and a variation through a statutory instrument that relates to EU law that has been carried across. That is important not just for lawmakers in your Lordships’ House, but also for the courts when they come to determine an issue. Given the volume of work they are likely to confront, certainly in the early stages, that is going to be extremely important.</p>
    <p pid="b262.0/5">It is a weird world—you wait for several weeks with an EU withdrawal Bill and all your amendments come at once. That seems to be my misfortune this morning. If the noble and learned Lord can give us some reassurances on the sort of information that is likely to be supplied with statutory instruments, I am minded not to debate Clause 17 stand part. In a sense, it is a follow-on, because in that debate I would hope to hear that the Minister would want to consider ensuring that when information is provided as background for statutory instruments, the appropriateness of that statutory instrument is very clearly spelled out. I am looking to hear from the Minister some other words of comfort on that issue. In those circumstances, I will not call for a debate on Clause 17 stand part.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.263.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.263.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.265.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.265.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.267.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.267.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.267.0" speakername="Lord Low of Dalston" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13876" colnum="267" time="11:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b267.0/1">My Lords, I am very grateful to all those who have spoken in support of my amendments; there has been very heavyweight support, if I may say so, from the noble and learned Lords, Lord Wallace of Tankerness, and Lord Goldsmith, and very valued support from the noble Lord, Lord Cashman. I also thank the Minister for his reply. Since he was kind enough to describe my amendments as “constructive”, it would be less than gracious if I did not say that I regarded his response as constructive. The Minister has recognised the need to look further at the scope of the explanatory statements provided for in the Bill, and I welcome that.</p>
    <p pid="b267.0/2">There is room for further discussion about the extent of the enabling powers in the Bill, which are underpinned in this legislation. The Minister thinks that my amendments go too far in the enabling powers that we are seeking to include, while I suggest that the Bill does not go far enough, so there may be some scope for meeting in the middle. Since the Minister has kindly undertaken to review the scope of the provisions in the Bill before Report, I hope he might agree that it would be beneficial if we could have further discussion to see whether there is not some common meeting ground in the middle so that we can go forward to Report in a spirit of unanimity. On that basis, I am happy to beg leave to withdraw the amendment.</p>
    <p pid="b267.0/3" class="italic">Amendment withdrawn.</p>
    <p pid="b267.0/4" class="italic">Amendments 243 to 251 not moved.</p>
    <p pid="b267.0/5" class="italic">Schedule 7 agreed.</p>
    <p pid="b267.0/6">       <b>         <i>Clause 17: Consequential and transitional provision</i>       </b>     </p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.267.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.267.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.267.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="267" time="11:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b267.1/1">Amendment 252</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.267.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.267.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.267.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.267.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.268.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.268.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.269.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.269.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.269.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.269.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.269.1" speakername="Lord Cormack" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10134" colnum="269" time="11:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b269.1/1">My Lords, I support strongly what the noble Lords, Lord Liddle and Lord Pannick, said. This is the underlying theme of the Committee stage of this Bill: what we are seeing is a proposed accretion of power to the Executive at the expense of Parliament. We have made this point numerous times over the past several days—it seems like years. It is crucial not only that my noble friend the Minister gives some recognition and assurances today—we can ask for no less—but that the Bill is amended, preferably by government amendment, before Report. I have said this many times, but if taking back control means anything, it means taking back control for Parliament and not for the Executive. The Government have to recognise, in a way that, sadly, my noble friend Lord Callanan, seemed incapable of recognising the other day, that Parliament is supreme and that, in particular, the other place is where the ultimate decision should be made.</p>
    <p pid="b269.1/2">I do not want us to be on a collision course with government. I hope that the Government, recognising the fundamental constitutional importance of these issues, will agree to accede to your Lordships’ Constitution Committee and delete this provision in Clause 17. It is incumbent on a Government who are concerned about the supremacy of Parliament to do precisely that and not to leave within the Bill a clause that gives, theoretically, untrammelled powers in many circumstances to Ministers. I hope that my noble friend will be able to give us some comforting words today but, however comforting the words may be, they will not be enough until this provision is removed from the Bill.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.269.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.269.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.269.2" speakername="Lord Lisvane" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25262" colnum="269" time="12:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b269.2/1">My Lords, I shall add to the compelling citation by my noble friend Lord Pannick of the Constitution Committee’s report what the Delegated Powers and Regulatory Reform Committee said about Clause 17. It pointed out that, unlike the regulation-making powers in Clauses 7 to 9, there is,</p>
    <p pid="b269.2/2" class="indent">“no time-limit on the making of regulations under clause 17”.</p>
    <p pid="b269.2/3">It also said that the powers to make consequential provision,</p>
    <p pid="b269.2/4" class="indent">“should be restricted by an objective test of necessity”.</p>
    <p pid="b269.2/5">That is the golden thread of appropriateness and necessity that has been running through a number of debates and I hope that a constructive way forward can be found on that before Report.</p>
    <p pid="b269.2/6">The Delegated Powers Committee also points out that, although paragraph 100 of the delegated powers memorandum says that the Henry VIII powers are appropriately conferred, and that,</p>
    <p pid="b269.2/7" class="indent">“a large number of ‘fairly straightforward’ changes, including to primary legislation, will be needed in consequence of this Bill … that does not explain why it is appropriate for the negative procedure to apply in all cases including those which are not ‘fairly straightforward’”.</p>
    <p pid="b269.2/8">The committee concluded:</p>
    <p pid="b269.2/9">“Where regulations under clause 17(1) amend or repeal primary legislation, the affirmative procedure should … apply in accordance with established practice”.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.270.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.270.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.270.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.270.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.271.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.271.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.271.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.271.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.272.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.272.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.272.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.272.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.272.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.272.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.273.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.273.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.273.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.273.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.273.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.273.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.274.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.274.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.274.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.274.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.274.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.274.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.274.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.274.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.274.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.274.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.274.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.274.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.274.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.274.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.275.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.275.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.275.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.275.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.275.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.275.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.275.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.275.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.275.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.275.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.275.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.275.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.276.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.276.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.276.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.276.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.276.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.276.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.276.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="276" time="12:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b276.2/1">Amendment 255</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.276.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.276.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.276.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.276.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.276.4" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13512" colnum="276" time="12:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b276.4/1">My Lords, this amendment and Amendment 364 follow the previous debate in the sense that they question powers that Ministers seek to take in the Bill which we in the Committee want to quiz and question and understand better. My concern is a simple one. Why do Ministers feel that they should have the right, and seek to have the right, to determine whether a piece of retained EU law should be designated as either, on the one hand, primary legislation or, on the other, secondary legislation?</p>
    <p pid="b276.4/2">I understand primary legislation, because it is what we deal with all the time. It is what we debate, consider, seek to amend, improve and all of those things. It is something over which we have much more control. When it comes to secondary legislation, as I said  earlier, it is not so easily amendable. You have to either take it or leave it. Sometimes we can regret it, but we cannot do much else with it. The Minister is seeking a power in Clause 17(1) that is extraordinarily helpful to the Government. It says, “Let’s just shove this into secondary legislation. They can’t amend it there or tinker with it. They either have to take it or leave it”.</p>
    <p pid="b276.4/3">That is an extraordinary powerful thing to be able to do if you are a Minister. I have sat in the seat that the noble and learned Lord sits in, and I am quite sure that I would have liked to have had that power from time to time. It would have been extraordinarily convenient and enabled us more speedily to get on with what we were seeking to do. I can think back to several Bills and subsequently Acts that I participated in putting on to the statute book and I can see how pleasant it must be to be able to do something rather more simply with secondary than with primary legislation.</p>
    <p pid="b276.4/4">We need to understand better exactly why the Minister feels that that clause is appropriate. The Constitution Committee raised this as an issue. Similarly, Amendment 364 is also in this group and handily co-signed by my noble friend Lord Pannick. That amendment seeks to remove paragraph 19 of Schedule 8, again on the recommendation of the Constitution Committee, because it relates to retained EU law which has been assigned the status of primary legislation.</p>
    <p pid="b276.4/5">We are looking for some clarification and transparency from the Minister on this because it seems an extraordinary power. He has helpfully quoted other pieces of legislation in earlier debates in aid of his argument about whether or not the powers that the Government are seeking under this piece of legislation are reasonable. Perhaps he can give some examples and explain to us the circumstances in which this particular power would be of value to this and other Governments. Maybe he can explain to us when it has been used in the past because that would at least enable us to understand the circumstances under which what on the face of it seems extraordinary would be acceptable. I am not happy about the powers sought here and neither was the Constitution Committee. For those reasons, I beg to move.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.277.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.277.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.278.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.278.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.278.0" speakername="Lord Pannick" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/14143" colnum="278" time="12:30:00" url="">
    <p pid="b278.0/1">My Lords, in the previous debate the Committee deliberated on the vice of Clause 17 (1). The amendment proposed by the noble Lord, Lord Bassam of Brighton, identifies a specific reason why Clause 17 (1) is so objectionable. When the Constitution Committee put to Ministers our concern, to which the noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay of Clashfern has just referred, that the Bill should identify the legal status of retained EU law, the answer from Ministers was that if necessary or appropriate they could use the powers conferred by Clause 17 (1) to designate what legal status retained EU law would have, and designate different parts of retained EU law for different purposes. The Constitution Committee made its view very clear in paragraph 69 of its report:</p>
    <p pid="b278.0/2">“It is constitutionally unacceptable for Ministers to have the power to determine something as fundamental as whether a part of our law should be treated as primary or secondary legislation”.</p>
    <p pid="b278.0/3">We debated what legal status should be given to retained EU law earlier in Committee. I respectfully agree with the observations made just now by the noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay of Clashfern. I emphasise, however, that it is the width of Clause 17 (1) that is so objectionable as it enables Ministers to assert that they could use it to make changes of such constitutional enormity to our legislation. I agree, therefore, with the concerns that the noble Lord, Lord Bassam of Brighton, has expressed.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.278.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.278.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.278.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.278.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.279.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.279.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.280.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.280.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.281.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.281.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.281.0" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13512" colnum="281" time="12:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b281.0/1">My Lords, I am intrigued by the Minister’s reply. I guess I shall have to look back at the debate on Amendment 33, which he referenced earlier, but I am far from satisfied on this point. While I have been sitting here, I have been thinking of an example of what Ministers can actually do with pieces of primary and secondary legislation, and one comes to mind.</p>
    <p pid="b281.0/2">Towards the end of our time in government, an amendment was passed in this House very much against my better judgment; I was rather horrified by it. It basically had the effect of enabling the Secretary of State to bring forward an order to give effect to the particular amendment. I went back to the department and said, “Look, this is terrible. We lost this vote in the House yesterday and it means that you will have to do something that we really do not want to do and that would be quite wrong”. The Secretary of State very simply said to me, “Don’t worry about it: I simply won’t bring forward the order”. That is a powerful position to be in if you are Secretary of State. The order was never forthcoming. I am sure there are many examples of a similar nature that will be adopted by Secretaries of State, not just now but in the future.</p>
    <p pid="b281.0/3">That thought in my mind makes me think that we may be giving a Secretary of State—a Minister—far too much by enabling them to decide what is and is not secondary and primary legislation. I do not know whether that was in the mind of the Constitution Committee when it particularly picked this out, but it was right to be alive to that concern. I was grateful for the support for the amendment from the noble and  learned Lord, Lord Mackay of Clashfern, because he is long experienced in these matters. He has a very wary and thoughtful eye on legislation and what it is.</p>
    <p pid="b281.0/4">I accept that we are in somewhat exceptional circumstances in that we are dealing with EU retained law, but the Minister will have got the message that we are very concerned and the concern is rather broad. In the end, what we put in primary legislation makes a difference and has the effect of changing people’s lives. Giving too much power to Ministers to determine what they can sneak in through secondary legislation, where we can do far less about it and do far less to improve its quality, is a proper constitutional concern that this House might express. For the moment, I beg leave to withdraw my amendment.</p>
    <p pid="b281.0/5" class="italic">Amendment 255 withdrawn.</p>
    <p pid="b281.0/6" class="italic">Amendments 256 to 260 not moved.</p>
    <p pid="b281.0/7" class="italic">Clause 17 agreed.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.282.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.282.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.282.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="282" time="12:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b282.0/1">Amendment 261</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.282.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.282.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.282.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.282.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.282.2" speakername="Lord Patten of Barnes" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13176" colnum="282" time="12:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b282.2/1">My Lords, this amendment is in my name and that of a number of other noble Lords. For many years, there has been a panel game on Radio 4 in which people are asked to speak about a subject of which they have not been  given notice for a minute without deviation or repetition. I have sometimes thought how that would cut short our debates in this House and down the Corridor. I have managed to avoid listening to this programme for the several decades that it has been broadcast, but others may know the one I am talking about.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/2">That may be a relevant point, given that we had an excellent debate on most of the issues that we are covering this morning only a week ago. It was an excellent debate in which we talked about the Northern Ireland border, the relationship between the Northern Ireland border and the Republic border in terms of economics and other issues. We talked about that border and its overall relationship with the European Union and the United Kingdom because it would be the only land border between the EU and the UK. And we talked about that whole issue in relation to the Good Friday agreement, which everybody accepts is one of the coping stones of the peace that has, thank heavens, returned to Northern Ireland for the past few years. There were a couple of notable speeches in that debate. The former most reverend Primate Emeritus of All Ireland made an extremely moving speech. I do not want to ruin his career, but the noble Lord who wound up the debate made an important and interesting speech as well.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/3">It reflected what has been said elsewhere. The noble Lord said in replying to that debate: “Let me be frank”. That is not always something that one expects Ministers to say and it sometimes invites the reply, “caveat emptor”. I certainly speak confessionally on that subject. He said “Let me be frank” and then he was. He said that,</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/4" class="indent">“the Belfast agreement remains the cornerstone of the United Kingdom Government’s policy as they approach Brexit. Further, the Belfast agreement is enshrined in international law, so it has a basis that is broader than simply membership of the EU. A number of noble Lords have made the point that it is our membership of the EU which was a factor in the agreement, and I do not think that that logic can be faulted”.—[<phrase class="offrep" id=", 14/3/18; col. 1703.]"><i>Official Report</i>, 14/3/18; col. 1703.]</phrase></p>
    <p pid="b282.2/5">He pointed out that in the light of that there was a great responsibility on our Government, on the Government in the Republic and on the EU to do all they can to sustain the Good Friday agreement and to find a solution to the question of the border.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/6">In saying that, I am sure that the noble Lord was aware that he was repeating what has been said by Mr Blair, Sir John Major, the former Taoiseach Bertie Ahern, and Senator George Mitchell, all of whom played a very important role in the Good Friday agreement, which is one of the biggest achievements in post-war British politics without any question at all. There are Members of this House who played a role in securing that outcome.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/7">Why is there a problem as we move down this path, like the chorus in “Fidelio”, into the sunlit realm of post-EU global Britain? There is a problem, for reasons which were explained very clearly. Some noble Lords used this quotation in the previous debate—quite simply, it is because of the challenge which the then Home Secretary referred to two days before the referendum when she said in reply to a question:</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/8">“Just think about it. If we are out of the European Union with tariffs on exporting goods into the EU there’d have be something to recognise that between Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland. And if you pulled out of the EU and came out of free movement, then how could you have a situation where there was an open border with a country that was in the EU and has access to free movement?”</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/9">I could not have put it better myself. Others have put it on both sides of the European referendum. It is the problem that the Government now have to address with some difficulty, because after the referendum result it was decided—I have read this in a book by the political editor of the Sunday Times, so it must be true—without any discussion or debate in Cabinet that whatever happened we would leave the single market and the customs union. So here we are, facing this very difficult problem.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/10">Some people have said, “Well, you can deal with it quite easily because there’s no need for a border”. We have been told that there are technological solutions. They do not yet exist. They are somewhere down the road. Most of the people who suggest them have never been to Northern Ireland and have no idea what Fermanagh, South Armagh and that borderland are actually like. They point to other countries that they say manage without borders or any of the infrastructure of borders, or customs controls. Curiously, they sometimes mention America and its borders. Tell that to President Trump. It does not feel border-free if you are building walls or trying to get goods from Canada into America or from America into Canada. They talk about Sweden and Norway. We know what the Swedish Minister said about that the other day when she said that it was easier to get to the moon than to get goods into Norway.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/11">Most experts have said very much the same thing, underlining the fact that borders, as we said during the earlier debate, are not principally about geography; they are partly about identity but they are also about the difference between legal regimes and regulatory regimes. I have to be careful about bringing a Frenchman into this debate, but somebody who perhaps knows more about trade negotiations than almost anybody—even more than Mr Fox—and who was Secretary-General of the WTO and before that a European Commissioner, is Pascal Lamy. In giving evidence in this House and in the House down the street, he said that,</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/12" class="indent">“at the moment the UK exits the customs union, there has to be a border”.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/13">He went on to say that “frictionless, invisible borders” are a “fairy tale”, and that a virtual border does not exist anywhere in the world.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/14">So we have an issue, and it is an issue that the British Government have not so far managed to resolve in our discussions with the European Union. Last week, we signed up to a backstop agreement on regulatory alignment, which we had signed up to in December and then denounced between when the European Union tried to put it into legal language earlier this week and the “consensus”—I think that is the word used by one of the Ministers for these things—in December.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/15">There is a real issue about this, and perhaps it is worth recalling why the Minister thinks that this is relevant to the Good Friday agreement. It is not because anybody  seriously believes that, if we do not resolve this, we will go straight back to the Troubles and see the sort of violence that some of us experienced in the 1960s, 1970s, 1980s and 1990s. However, the chief constable of the Northern Ireland Police Service does think that if there is a hard border of any sort and there are customs officers, they will become a target for violence. That is not condoning that, it is just pointing out reality in the context of Northern Ireland and the Republic. Of course any sort of border would have an impact on the trade between Northern Ireland and the Republic, and we know what the Good Friday agreement says about the importance of that economic relationship.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/16">There is another area in which a border would have a profound effect on the continued integrity of the Good Friday agreement: the question of identity. As was said in our last debate, at the heart of the Good Friday agreement is a proposition that is difficult to put into practice—and it says a great deal for the negotiators of the Good Friday agreement that they managed it. People who had previously condoned and taken part in violence to try to change the constitutional arrangements in Northern Ireland accepted that, from now on, those arrangements could be changed only through the ballot box by constitutional means and with democratic accountability. In return for that, they were assured that their own sense of identity and loyalties could be expressed with the encouragement and endorsement of the authorities. For example, if they were republican, they no longer had to sign up to all the manifestations and symbols of a unionist state. They could be Irish or British, or they could be Irish, British and European, and they would not have a border as a symbol between the Republic of Ireland and Northern Ireland or between Britain and the Republic of Ireland. The Good Friday agreement is profoundly affected by what happens to the border.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/17">Presumably recognising that, the Secretary of State for Brexit said after the negotiations the other day that it is,</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/18" class="indent">“our intention to achieve a partnership that is so close as to not require specific measures in relation to Northern Ireland”.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/19">Well, I can help him. There is a partnership that is available straightaway: go back to the customs union; join the single market. That will solve the question of the Northern Ireland border.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/20">I am rather nervous about predictions. My favourite English footballer was Paul Gascoigne, who, having been asked on one occasion at half time to say what the result of the match would be, said, “I never make predictions, and I never will”. But one prediction I make is this: before this political jihad is over, before we have finished with this, we will be back in the customs union. We will get back into the customs union partly because I think that is what we will vote for in this House, but, even more so, because that is what enough people will have the courage to vote for down the Corridor.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/21">But let us suppose that that does not happen, solving the problem of the border, as they say, at a stroke. Then there is a very strong case for belt and braces. If you are the emperor with no clothes, belt and braces may seem a little curious. But there is a very strong argument—just in case we do not find  other ways of solving the border, the technology is not available or the blue skies are a little clouded—to write into the Bill the terms, provisions, values and objectives of the Good Friday agreement. What is not to like? It would not damage anything or anybody. It is an assertion of what, apparently, we all believe—that the Good Friday agreement has to be kept at all costs—unless you are a former Conservative Secretary of State and think that the Good Friday agreement could be changed, thrown out or forgotten about, which I do not think is the view of this House, even it is the view of a couple of Brexiteer former Secretaries of State. It should be easy for the Minister, who was so frank and helpful in his last intervention, to simply say that we will write the Good Friday agreement, as Amendment 261 suggests, into the Bill.</p>
    <p pid="b282.2/22">There may be some reason why the Minister does not have the authority to do that this morning. I was going to say that we have not had any of the duty privy counsellor Bench of Brexiteers here today, but I can see one. I am glad that they still do morning shifts. Even with just one here, he may have some difficulty in giving us the sort of assurance that we might like. But I very much hope that, if that is the case, the majority of Members of the House will come back on Report and make absolutely certain that we write the terms of the Good Friday agreement into the Bill if, by then, we have not had a satisfactory response on the border. I beg to move.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.286.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.286.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.288.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.288.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.289.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.289.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.290.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.290.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.291.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.291.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.291.0" speakername="Lord Eames" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/12995" colnum="291" time="13:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b291.0/1">My Lords, the temperature of our debate this afternoon reflects again the emotions expressed so recently in this House by those of us who live, work and have our being in Northern Ireland. We are sensitive as a people to the fact that your Lordships’ House is hearing on repeated occasions references to “our” problems and “our” difficulties. But this is taking on a different dimension, because what was traditionally our problem is becoming a problem on a much wider scale, for it is becoming the crux of the debate on the withdrawal of the United Kingdom as a nation from the EU.</p>
    <p pid="b291.0/2">The problems to which the Good Friday/Belfast agreement has done so much to provide an ongoing solution are so often taken to be not just a matter for the people of Northern Ireland but now central to what people are considering. The difficulty of the border, community relations, human rights—all that long list of human problems was once contained within the borders of Northern Ireland but, as the noble Lord, Lord Patten, so rightly reminded us a few minutes ago, it is becoming crucial to the debate on the future of our withdrawal. None of us wants to apologise to this House for the fact that our local problems now take on international significance. When we listen once more to the experience of former Secretaries of State for Northern Ireland, we are reminded that the problems to which I have referred have taken on a dimension that we never envisaged, even at the height of the Troubles.</p>
    <p pid="b291.0/3">For that reason, when I read Amendment 261 in the name of the noble Lord, Lord Patten, I began to wonder whether we were stating the obvious yet again. Are we stating the fact that the importance of the Belfast agreement is such that it is welcome to see it suggested as a part of the Bill? I began to wonder whether other issues deteriorate the importance of reference to the Belfast principles, et cetera. Then I listened a few minutes ago to a debate on another amendment, when we concentrated on giving what someone said were excessive powers to Ministers to look at secondary legislation and have wide-ranging powers to alter the details of policy without addressing the power and supremacy of Parliament. I began to wonder: is it possible to visualise the situation in years to come when something as sensitive as the Belfast agreement—something as sensitive as all that the agreement has achieved—could possibly be affected by what we listened to in that previous discussion.</p>
    <p pid="b291.0/4">At the back of all the detail we are looking at are the fundamental questions of what a devolved Administration is and what should be the relationship between the mother of Parliaments and the devolved Administrations. For that reason, I found I had sympathy for the wording of this amendment, for it is a safeguard to the sensitivities mentioned by the noble Lords, Lord Patten and Lord Murphy, which are very close to my heart having been through the whole process of the peace movement in Northern Ireland.</p>
    <p pid="b291.0/5">The noble Lord, Lord Patten, attributed me as an “emeritus” this morning—a new description. Many things have been said about me in the past, but I thank him for this new honour. Emeritus I may be, but I am also speaking from my heart and from my experience of a lifetime working, I hope, in the building of bridges in Northern Ireland. For that reason, I find myself supporting the thrust of what this amendment seeks to do. I urge sensitive expression and appreciation of the amendment by your Lordships’ House.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.292.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.292.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.293.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.293.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.293.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.293.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.293.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.293.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.295.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.295.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.296.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.296.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.296.0" speakername="Lord Alderdice" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13371" colnum="296" time="13:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b296.0/1">My Lords, I am very grateful to the noble Lord, Lord Patten of Barnes, not only for the passionate and articulate way in which he introduced the debate on this group of amendments—particularly Amendment 261—but also for the lifetime of commitment that he has given to the issues of Northern Ireland. That length of commitment speaks a great deal to me, as someone from that part of the United Kingdom.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/2">As the fourth musketeer, as it were, I want to say something slightly different about why I think this amendment is not just important but critical. On <phrase class="date" code="2018-12-06">6 December</phrase> last year, on the fifth day in Committee, Lady Hermon, the honourable Member for North Down, spoke about the key principles of the Belfast agreement in an amendment almost identical to this one. When the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Exiting the EU, Mr Robin Walker, responded, he kept talking about the agreement, the commitment to the agreement, and the way the agreement was backed up. Lady Hermon came back to him saying that the issue was not the agreement but the principles, and he really did not seem to get it, because he kept coming back to saying that they were committed to the agreement and would ensure that the agreement was there.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/3">I want to say why I would go even further than the noble Lord, Lord Patten of Barnes, in saying that it is not just a question of whether this would be a problem or harmful but why this is absolutely essential not that  the precise wording of all the amendment is included, but that the principles of the Belfast agreement are included. I shall explain why.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/4">We have had many decades of trying to get agreements in Northern Ireland. We have had them before, and they did not work as a peace process, because they did not address the key disturbed historic relationships in these islands. In many ways, this was the understanding that the European project stepped out with, with Monnet, Schuman, Adenauer and so on. They understood that it was the relationships between the different countries and communities that were essential—and, as we know, the whole complicated edifice was created in which there could be co-operation.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/5">One frustration for me is that colleagues who, like myself, are committed to remain, have failed to address the question of why, after 40 years, one of the parties is seeking divorce and many others are very uncertain about whether they want to stick with it. My own view is that, as time went on and we moved from the first generation of those who were committed to those who were there later, we moved from the things that were put in place as the instruments to ensure the fundamental purpose of the project, which was to stop war and build relationships. The instruments were things such as the market, the common currency, and the opportunity for European political leaders to be at the top table of global affairs. Those instruments became the purpose of the exercise for many of those who were involved. When in any set of relationships the instruments of the relationship become a substitute for the purpose of the relationship, the relationship is already beginning to fail.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/6">My concern is about the commitment to the Belfast agreement, a legislative agreement with a commitment to certain kinds of constitutional and institutional matters and a commitment, as the noble Lord, Lord Patten, knows well, to changes in the administration of justice and changing policing—all the important things, including the things that are mentioned in the other amendment about human rights. Those things will not keep the relationships alive, if we forget that the relationships are the key issue. That is why I want to see the principles written into the Bill.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/7">When I was involved in the process, we came to a point of understanding this in a very long and painful way. Most of those with whom I was involved are no longer involved politically, or even around at all. As I look around, I see those political leaders who represent the three key relationships not understanding what it was about—the relationship between political leaders in Northern Ireland. We are a long way from the relationships between the David Trimble, and Seamus Mallon, never mind those between Ian Paisley and Martin McGuinness. Let us not forget that Dr Paisley was not too keen about the Belfast agreement when it came out in the first instance. But the relationship between the political leaders in Northern Ireland does not have the same constructive engagement now. In the relationship between north and south, we are being pulled apart—sometimes by those who say that they want to unite the island. What about the relationship between London and Dublin, between the British and Irish Prime Ministers? Think back to the kind of  relationship there was between John Major and Albert Reynolds, or between Tony Blair and Bertie Ahern. We do not have that kind of relationship in either direction.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/8">The European Union itself was the model and the inspiration; it was the container for the relationships that kept the British and Irish Governments together and working, so that when John Major and Albert Reynolds became Prime Ministers, they had already been Finance Ministers and worked together, and they said, “We know it’s impossible but we’re going to have a go”.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/9">Another thing is that, if many of those in Brussels, and indeed in London and Dublin, who are saying that this and that is impossible had been around in Belfast 20 years ago, there would have been no Good Friday agreement, because they would have said, “It doesn’t fit in with our understandings of sovereignty”. Even on the rule of law, think of the people who would never have been let out of prison if others had simply stuck with the understanding of the rule of law as it was then. We had to be more adventurous and creative, just like you have to be in any relationship if it is to evolve, change, develop and, frankly, survive. When a Minister says, “But we are committed to the Belfast agreement”, I do not doubt that. Even when he or she says, “It’s implied in the legislation”, I do not disagree with that. But I do disagree with the idea that we do not have to put it in black and white, firmly and clearly, that the principles of the Belfast agreement and the relationship approach are critical and they need to be in the Bill.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/10">I have spent a lot of my life going to other parts of the world. I am not long back from Colombia, where they have a peace process; just before that I was in India, and in a week or so’s time I will be out in Peru. In all those places, they are not looking to the Northern Ireland arrangements and the Irish peace process because they want our particular constitution or institutions, or our way of dealing with policing and the administration of justice. They are looking at the underlying fundamental principle, which was our discovery, that these problems were ones of relationships—historic, disturbed relationships between communities of people—and that we had to find ways of addressing that creatively. Whatever kind of mechanisms we used, that was what it was about.</p>
    <p pid="b296.0/11">As I look around at home, coming up to the 20th anniversary, I see a whole generation of young political leaders who do not get that. They think it is all just about doing politics, like people do everywhere, and it is not. We need to put this into the Bill to make it absolutely clear to anyone who comes back to the question that, in the absence of that containing environment of the EU, which made it possible for us—I say that because it is very doubtful that we would have got the Belfast agreement without the context of the EU—we have to emphasise with even greater clarity than before the fundamental basis on which that agreement was reached. We have to hope and work and pray that we can work to find a way of maintaining those relationships and developing them through the stormy waters which undoubtedly lie ahead.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.299.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.299.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.299.0" speakername="Lord Carswell" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/12842" colnum="299" time="14:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b299.0/1">My Lords, I had not intended to intervene in this debate, partly because I was not present at Second Reading. I apologise to your Lordships for that but there were certain problems that I had at home. But I am impelled to do so by what has been said so very eloquently by many of your Lordships today.</p>
    <p pid="b299.0/2">I have lived the whole of my life in Belfast and been through a considerable amount in that time. I have lived there even longer than my noble and right reverend friend Lord Eames, whom I have known, liked, respected and admired—no less so today—for many years of that time. I have known the noble Lord, Lord Alderdice, and I like and respect what he has had to say. I am very happy to support the principles of what they have both said. I will come back to what I mean by “the principles” in a moment.</p>
    <p pid="b299.0/3">I was very close, personally and professionally, to what we have referred to by the usual euphemism as the Troubles. It was a dreadful time and I would hate with every fibre of my being to think that we might go back to that. The fact that we have had peace—maybe not perfect, but a great deal better than what we had before—for 20 years now has been of great importance in the life of the Province. That it should continue is also of great importance, not merely because it gives a better approach to normal life in the Province but because it conditions people to feel that that is the proper way to conduct their lives, which of course it is. If the continuance of the Belfast agreement helps in that, then I am emphatically on the side of those who say that it should be taken account of.</p>
    <p pid="b299.0/4">The only caveat I have is on the wording. The Belfast principles include certain things, uncontestably, but what else? A great deal of my professional life, both at the Bar and on the Bench, was spent in interpreting statutory wording and attempting to find its proper and expressed meaning—the way in which statutes should be approached—while trying to see either loopholes or where other people would look for loopholes. That is the great problem in drafting anything, particularly something as important as this. Therefore, that is the only reason I issue a note of warning. I would be perfectly happy to see a clause of the nature proposed on the statute book. But if it is to be done, I simply warn that defining the Belfast principles, or leaving them undefined, could allow the wording to be put to purposes which we might not think of today but which some other people will think of at some time. I leave this thought with the Minister who is replying and with your Lordships.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.299.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.299.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.300.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.300.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.300.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.300.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.300.1" speakername="Baroness Smith of Basildon" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10546" colnum="300" time="14:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b300.1/1">My Lords, as my noble friend Lord Bassam said, this has been an immensely interesting debate. I know that other noble Lords have referred to this as the second debate that we have had on Northern Ireland, but all the amendments in this group reflect the concerns that we have had, the degree of concern around the issue and the fact that we have not really had the answers to satisfy those concerns yet. The impact of Brexit on the Good Friday or Belfast agreement is profound. I understand that the Minister has a weariness about saying the same things as last time, but I hope that he will understand, from comments that I shall make now and that other noble Lords have made, why there is a need to return to these issues.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/2">My noble friend Lord Bassam sums up in his amendment—which is entirely reasonable, and I hope that the Minister can accept it—that this is about the Government assessing the impact and publishing that. I go back to the speech made by the noble Lord, Lord Patten of Barnes, and his amendment, to which I have added my name. He referred to the radio programme “Just a Minute”, and I think that that is quite apt: this issue deserves “repetition”, and the Government should show “hesitation” and reflect, and perhaps come back with some “deviation”, moving from their current position and giving us some answers as to how the issue can be addressed.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/3">There has been some journey from the Government to clarify the status of the December joint report on the progress of phase 1. Where the Government stand on regulatory alignment has been almost like a political hokey-cokey, and the current position, which is a backstop for what could happen, is probably fair. But the impact of a hard border in Northern Ireland would be profound and deep and have implications for the peace process. It is not just about the physical border—it is also about the psychological impact that it would have, and I think all noble Lords who have spoken today have understood that. The noble Lord, Lord Patten, referred to the security implications, as I did last week, of what would physically happen if there were a hard border and how those border points would be guarded.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/4">Look at the logic of the issue of trade and the hard border. The Government say that there should be regulatory alignment and they accept it between the Republic of Ireland and Northern Ireland. However, if you move on from that, the Republic of Ireland obviously has regulatory alignment with the EU, and Northern Ireland has regulatory alignment with the rest of Great Britain, so, surely, that would mean that there has to be regulatory alignment throughout the whole of that area, which to my mind sounds something like a customs union. I really do not understand why the Government have set their face against this and made it one of their red lines.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/5">I discussed this with a senior government Minister recently and said that the lack of detail on this issue to your Lordship’s House and generally is why it has become such an issue. His view was that the statements made by the Minister and the Prime Minister about the need for a soft border, the absolute commitment from the Government to the Good Friday agreement, and the total rejection of a hard border are clear. I agree, but the noble Baroness, Lady O’Neill, hit the nail on the head with exactly the point that I made to that Minister at the time—how will it be done? Until the Government can say how, we remain in a sort of no-man’s land or Alice in Wonderland situation as to how it will happen. I was told that the Government could not say how they would do it until negotiations take place. But if it is a matter for negotiation, how are the Government able to make that commitment? I must say to the Minister that it is an unacceptable position to be in.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/6">This may not satisfy all noble Lords, but to remain in a customs union would be part of the solution to this. The Government reject that and say that it is a red line that they cannot go beyond, but if they maintain that red line, I still cannot understand—trust me, I have tried really hard to—how the Government can achieve their objectives alongside it. We heard suggestions in the debates last week and from other noble Lords this morning about how that can be done, but I say to the Minister that it is the Government’s responsibility to tell us how it can be achieved. We need clarity, detail and to move beyond the warm words. We want something to happen and we have to make it happen.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/7">The Minister and the Prime Minister have been clear and I do not doubt their sincerity in the statements they have made, but why are we having this debate? It is because saying something does not make it true or make it happen. There has to be legislative certainty around this issue. It is that legislative certainty that we are still waiting for and need to see. The amendment in the name of the noble Lord, Lord Patten of Barnes, is one way forward. If the Minister has a better suggestion and wants to bring forward a government amendment to address the issue, I would be very happy to see it. But in the absence of that, we will have to press this through our own amendment.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/8">My noble friends Lady Lister, Lord Judd and Lord Cashman raise in their Amendment 308ZA the issue of the equivalence of rights on a north-south basis as being a defining feature of this agreement, and they referred to the essential nature of the Charter of Fundamental Rights. Again, we have a Government red line about that charter. I fail to understand that. Some red lines, such as the one about the agencies and the involvement of the ECJ, have been smudged a little pink now. Is this another red line that needs to be smudged pink? The Charter of Fundamental Rights is, bizarrely, the only specific exclusion in terms of the existing rights of citizens. That has a huge impact on those in Northern Ireland. My noble friend Lady Lister has raised this question before, but how can the Government ensure equivalence of rights without that charter? She gave examples of real people, problems and issues. Unless we can give real answers to those people, we will find ourselves again in a vacuum of being able to give assurances.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/9">My noble friend Lord Murphy of Torfaen brought to his comments not only his knowledge and experience but the great affinity he has with Northern Ireland through his service, both as Minister of State and—I would say this as one of his junior Ministers—a first-rate Secretary of State. He focused on the equality and human rights issues and backed up entirely what my noble friend Lady Lister was saying. These are central to the integrity of the agreement. We cannot fudge that or move away from it. We have to respect that integrity. The agreement was hard-fought, as those who were there at the time and involved would say. The Government have to respond to the details that he provided and the specific points around the fundamental principles. If the Minister cannot respond, there has to be discussion so that we get to a point that is in the right place.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/10">I finish on the comments of the noble and right reverend Lord, Lord Eames, on Amendment 261. As always, he brings to these debates both his life experience and a passionate commitment. I recall—as did the noble Lord, Lord Cormack—the Eames-Bradley report, by the noble Lord, Lord Eames and the great Dennis Bradley. Both of them, in taking it through, were prepared to think the unthinkable, to do the right thing and to take on those challenging and difficult issues for the greater good. At times that was uncomfortable and not easy, but he did it. He is due the respect of this House: it should heed his words on these issues today.</p>
    <p pid="b300.1/11">The Minister has been clear on his commitment—which I do not doubt—to the Good Friday agreement, but I doubt that we have what the House and the legislation needs: the legislative certainty on the issue that gives us the confidence that the commitment will be not just in words but in deeds and legislation.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.303.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.303.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.303.0" speakername="Lord Duncan of Springbank" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25713" colnum="303" time="14:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b303.0/1">My Lords, this has been a wide-ranging debate and I begin by thanking the noble Lord, Lord Patten of Barnes, for facilitating it. It will be almost impossible for me to respond without some form of repetition, I am afraid, and I am nearly certain that I cannot do it within one minute—I am very aware of that. Last week, too, we had a wide-ranging debate that touched on a number of issues and I hope that noble Lords will have an opportunity to examine some of the answers and discussions. I will try to be as focused as I can in the time available.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/2">One of my first repetitions—one that I cannot make often enough—is that the Belfast agreement is the cornerstone of the UK Government’s policy and so it will remain. It is important to stress that the United Kingdom Government and the Ministers in the devolved Administration are already bound in statute and treaty under international law as an obligation of that Belfast agreement. That binds not just the United Kingdom Government but also the Irish Government, so this matter rests comfortably in that space.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/3">Amendment 261, in the name of the noble Lord, Lord Patten of Barnes, would require both Ministers and Northern Ireland departments to have regard to the Belfast agreement and the wider principles when making any provision under this Bill that affects Northern Ireland. Those wider principles have been mentioned a number of times, not least by the noble Lord, Lord Alderdice.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/4">Subsection (3) would require the Secretary of State to refuse consent to reserved provisions under devolved legislations unless the provision is necessary only as a direct consequence of the UK’s exit from the EU. This would place a much greater constraint on a provision that could be made for Northern Ireland compared to the rest of the UK, even in circumstances where there was no impact whatever on the Belfast agreement. In the same vein, the Secretary of State would be prevented from making any consequential provision affecting Northern Ireland beyond the minimum strictly required only as a direct consequence of exit. That would  substantially constrain what could be done to update the statute book in Northern Ireland, putting the jurisdiction at a disadvantage compared to the rest of the UK. That is why we would not be able to move forward on the amendment as it has been tabled.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/5">I am conscious as we approach the 20th anniversary—the noble Lord, Lord Murphy, stressed this—that we wish to see major progress, not least in the formation of an Executive. However, the noble Lord and other noble Lords raised wider issues, not least criminal proceedings and the European arrest warrant. In this context, I am conscious of the “beasts” of the noble Baroness, Lady O’Neill. Each of these elements will form part of the ongoing sector-specific elements which we will be discussing and which will come before your Lordships’ House for that thorough examination.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/6">Amendment 316, tabled by the noble Lord, Lord Bassam, relates to an issue that has also been raised by your Lordships’ Constitution Committee. I say to the noble Lord that we will take on board his thoughts and give due consideration both to the Committee’s report and to the issues that he has raised. We are conscious of that as a factor.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/7">As to the Charter of Fundamental Rights, the noble Baroness, Lady Lister, has raised this wider issue on a number of occasions, as she reminded us, and I feel ill-equipped compared to those who responded to the point in the past. I will make two statements in direct response. The noble Baroness mentioned that next week there will be a delegation from Northern Ireland. I will be very happy to meet them, if that can be facilitated. I also give a commitment that I will take away her remarks from today and give them due consideration.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/8">I could be repetitious at this point and say the lines that noble Lords have previously been given in response. I can give them again, but I think that noble Lords will appreciate that they will broadly stand where they did in the past. However, I am happy to engage directly with the noble Baroness and the noble Lord, Lord Cashman, on these matters going forward. I hope that that will give some comfort, if not contentment, on this matter.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/9">I am always aware of what the noble and right reverend Lord, Lord Eames, brings to the debate. I think that he has captured the mood of the House as I do not doubt he has captured the mood of the entire island of Ireland in the past. His points are none the less correct. There is no doubt that the issues that we are facing now on Ireland will be the crux of the ongoing discussion. It is right that the noble Baroness, Lady Smith, should have raised these points again in her remarks. She is absolutely correct when she says that we have a responsibility to tell this House what we will be moving forward. We will fulfil that responsibility. It will not be in the withdrawal Bill per se. The purpose of the withdrawal Bill is to create a functional statute book for day one after Brexit. However, for each of the elements that has been raised, not least those that are sector-specific, we will come back to the House with clear statements, which all noble Lords will have the opportunity to address. I hope that we can make that point going forward as best we can.</p>
    <p pid="b303.0/10">I am aware that a number of other noble Lords have raised important issues, not least my noble friend Lord Cormack, the noble Lord, Lord Jay of Ewelme, and the noble Baroness, Lady O’Neill of Bengarve. This has been a wide-ranging debate. I hope that there will be some comfort in my words, but I appreciate that they may not be as comfortable as the Committee would like them to be. On that basis, I hope that the noble Lord will feel able to withdraw the amendment.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.305.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.305.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.305.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.305.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.305.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.305.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.305.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.305.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.306.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.306.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.306.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.306.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.306.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.306.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.306.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.306.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.306.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.306.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.307.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.307.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.307.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.307.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.307.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.307.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.307.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.307.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.307.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.307.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.307.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.307.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.307.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.307.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.308.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.308.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.308.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.308.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.308.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.308.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.308.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.308.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.308.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.308.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.308.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.308.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.308.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.308.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.308.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.308.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.309.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.309.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.309.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.309.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.309.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.309.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.309.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.309.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.309.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.309.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.309.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.309.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.309.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.309.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.309.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.309.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.310.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.310.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.310.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.310.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.310.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.310.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.310.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.310.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.310.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.310.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.310.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.310.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.310.5" speakername="Lord Ahmad of Wimbledon" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25040" colnum="310" time="15:08:00" url="">
    <p pid="b310.5/1">The noble Lord speaks from vast experience in this respect, and I agree with him. I would add that we can learn from the valuable experience of all 53 nations. The approach of Her Majesty’s Government, and indeed mine as a Minister on human rights, has never been one of pointing fingers. It is about learning from experience. Our own journey on gender equality, on LGBT rights and the  broader spectrum of human rights has been one where we have learned from example and through sharing experiences, whether we do it with other countries or countries do it with us. That is the value of the Commonwealth network.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.311.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.311.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.311.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.311.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.311.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.311.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.311.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.311.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.311.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.311.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.311.4" speakername="Lord O'Shaughnessy" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25458" colnum="311" time="15:16:00" url="">
    <p pid="b311.4/1">I thank congratulate the noble Baroness on her tenacity in raising the issue and thank her for giving me the opportunity to meet parents whose children use these services. First, it is incredibly important to be clear that there are rules for how the consultations that the judicial review said should be held should take place, and they must be abided by. More importantly, as I have just set out, there are legal obligations under the 2014 Act for joint commissioning between the CCG and the local authority. That is not one telling the other what to do; it is joint commissioning. Most important of all—the point that the noble Baroness makes—is that whenever these bodies are planning for the future, they have to keep the needs of the children in mind. That is what we, whether it is NHS England or the department, are imploring them to do through this process. Indeed, they are obliged to do that.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.312.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.312.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.312.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.312.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.312.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.312.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.312.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.312.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.312.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.312.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.312.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.312.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.312.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.312.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.313.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.313.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.313.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.313.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.313.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.313.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.313.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.313.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.313.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.313.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.313.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.313.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.313.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.313.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.313.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.313.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.314.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.314.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.314.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.314.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.314.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.314.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.314.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.314.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.314.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.314.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.314.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.314.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.315.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.315.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.315.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.315.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.315.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.315.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.315.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.315.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.315.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.315.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.315.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.315.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.315.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.315.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.315.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.315.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.316.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.316.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.316.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.316.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.316.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.316.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.316.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.316.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.316.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="316" time="15:31:00" url="">
    <p pid="b316.3/1">Amendment 266</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.316.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.316.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.316.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.316.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.318.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.318.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.318.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.318.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.318.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.318.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.318.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.318.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.319.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.319.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.319.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.319.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.319.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.319.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.320.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.320.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.321.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.321.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.321.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.321.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.321.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.321.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.321.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.321.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.321.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.321.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.321.4" speakername="Lord Hope of Craighead" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13079" colnum="321" time="15:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b321.4/1">My Lords, I am grateful to the Minister for her remarks. The use of the expression “sub-delegation” gives some insight into the thinking of the Government. As was pointed out, “delegation” is not an appropriate word to use where matters have already been devolved—by the statutes to which I referred earlier—to both Wales and Scotland. “Sub-delegation” is a very odd word to use. We are talking about a power within the devolved competencies for the devolved authorities to legislate, or confer a power to legislate, by whatever means they think appropriate. So I am encouraged by the fact that the Minister is prepared to look at this again. I think that she will agree with me that what much of what we will be discussing in this little group of amendments is work  in progress, as we try to work through the detail of the scheme that the Bill sets out. I am encouraged by her reply.</p>
    <p pid="b321.4/2">I also thank all those who have contributed to this brief debate. On the word “adjustment”, I refer to what the noble Lady, Baroness Hayter, was saying. The Minister will remember, from her early days in the law in Scotland, that the word “adjustment” is sometimes used to take things out as well as to put things in. It is a word that came naturally to me as a means of dealing with bits in the statute that require to be trimmed, perhaps by removal, as well as by refining the language. I am grateful to the noble Lords, Lord Thomas of Gresford and Lord Hennessy of Nympsfield, for their emphasis that we are dealing with matters of great significance and importance. When I said that these were just technical points, I did not mean to suggest otherwise; rather, I was suggesting that the main thrust of our argument will be reserved for when we come to look at the Government’s amendments.</p>
    <p pid="b321.4/3">Lastly, on the contribution of the noble Baroness, Lady Finlay of Llandaff, I join in her tribute to the efforts that the noble Lord, Lord Bourne, is making to discuss matters with us and to reach as much common ground as possible. I, too, have had useful meetings with him and I am grateful to him and to his team for the attention they have given to the points I have been raising. As I have said, this is work in progress; I am encouraged by what the Minister said and, in the light of that, I beg leave to withdraw my amendment.</p>
    <p pid="b321.4/4" class="italic">Amendment 266 withdrawn.</p>
    <p pid="b321.4/5" class="italic">Amendment 267 had been withdrawn from the Marshalled List.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.322.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.322.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.322.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="322" time="15:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b322.0/1">Amendment 268</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.322.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.322.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.322.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.322.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.322.2" speakername="Lord Hope of Craighead" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13079" colnum="322" time="15:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b322.2/1">My Lords, this is the first of another group of amendments, all of which are in my name. Amendment 268 refers to a provision in paragraph 4 of Part 1 of the schedule, which states that no regulations made under that part by a devolved authority prevent it from conferring functions that correspond to functions under EU tertiary legislation. Amendment 296 relates to the same restriction, which we find in paragraph 24. Amendments 280 and 294 deal with another restriction—that no regulations  may be made under that part by a devolved authority which modify any retained direct EU legislation or anything which is retained law by virtue of Clause 4.</p>
    <p pid="b322.2/2">These are rather complicated matters to explain, but they are all examples of restrictions on the power of the devolved authorities to do what they are supposed to do under Part 1 of the schedule in the two respects mentioned in these passages. The whole point is the same one I mentioned before in regard to the previous group—that these are restrictions on actions which otherwise would be taken within devolved competence.  The fact that there are restrictions at all is contrary to the philosophy on which the devolution system has been based. It is a given—as we have seen already in the passage I read out earlier—that, if the powers are exercised, they can be exercised only within the devolved area. There is no question of their moving into the reserved areas as that is not within their competence; if the matter is within their competence, the argument is that they should not be inhibited from doing what they consider to be right.</p>
    <p pid="b322.2/3">Tertiary legislation is an animal that has not been referred to much in our debates in this Committee. A fairly lengthy definition of it is to be found on page 10 of the Bill, but it is not obvious to me why the devolved authorities should not be able to deal with tertiary EU legislation in the same way as any other EU retained legislation. So, with that rather brief introduction, directed particularly to Amendment 268, I beg to move.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.323.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.323.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.324.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.324.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.324.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.324.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.324.1" speakername="Lord Thomas of Gresford" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/12974" colnum="324" time="16:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b324.1/1">Your Lordships should appreciate that the devolved Administrations can make law but have been constrained by EU law in the areas of their competencies. If EU law is taken away, we would expect the devolved Administrations to carry on without that constraint. Previously, there had been no constraint on their making law within their competencies from Westminster, only from Brussels. Taking away Brussels suddenly imposes Westminster constraints on the devolved Administrations in areas such as agriculture, which have been devolved to them, but it also means that the devolved Administrations cannot make any changes to the law at all—even when it is, for example, an agricultural matter. It is not simply taking away the constraint of Brussels, but imposing something entirely new. Westminster politics comes into it then; considerations that have not emerged into the arena before suddenly become important. That is why these are matters of principle and deeply difficult to resolve.</p>
    <p pid="b324.1/2">I was so pleased to hear the noble Lord, Lord Hennessey, say that this was such a difficult area because I suggested in my Second Reading speech that we should have taken devolution completely out of the Bill. At that point, the Government would have had no problem in getting legislative consent from Scotland and Wales and could have sorted out devolution issues as a completely separate matter. Now, your Lordships are listening—in the context of the EU (Withdrawal) Bill—to a very difficult issue.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.325.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.325.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.325.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.325.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.326.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.326.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.327.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.327.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.327.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="327" time="16:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b327.0/1">Amendment 274</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.327.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.327.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.327.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.327.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.328.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.328.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.328.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.328.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.328.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.328.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.329.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.329.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.329.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="329" time="16:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b329.0/1">Oh!</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.329.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.329.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.329.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.329.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.329.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.329.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.329.3" speakername="Lord Wigley" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10635" colnum="329" time="16:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b329.3/1">My Lords, I will strike a different note as I put forward what are perhaps the substantive arguments—as we see them—in relation to these issues.</p>
    <p pid="b329.3/2">Amendment 304 has for some reason been grouped with these amendments, which does not make an awful lot of sense. It stands in my name and that of my noble friend Lord Hain, and is based on one of the key amendments drafted by the Welsh and Scottish Governments ahead of the Bill’s passage through the other place. That amendment is also covered by part of Amendment 303, which surprisingly will not arise until very late tonight. None the less, Amendment 304 goes to the heart of the widespread criticism of Clause 11 as it currently stands—I am aware that amendments may come forward later—and lifts the restriction it places on the devolved parliaments in relation to EU retained law.</p>
    <p pid="b329.3/3">My fear—and that of all parties in the National Assembly—is that giving UK Ministers control in the EU withdrawal Bill over areas of retained EU law relating to matters which fall under devolved competences will, in effect, tend to normalise direct rule from Westminster in these areas. Given the powers under this and other recent legislation which enable Ministers at Westminster to amend devolved legislation by order, this will, in effect, undermine Welsh sovereignty in areas which are devolved to Wales and blur the responsibility of the National Assembly. Furthermore, there is a fear that this will set a precedent for this and future UK Governments, who may well be tempted when a devolved Government act in a way with which they disagree, to find a justification to intervene. This would be particularly galling if it were on issues where Welsh interests were seen to be in conflict with England’s perceived interests—perhaps validly so. The Prime  Minster has, of course, pledged never again to “devolve and forget”. That can be interpreted in more than one way, and in this context it has generated quite a few ripples of unease.</p>
    <p pid="b329.3/4">In order to persuade the devolved parliaments to agree to legislative consent orders—which are currently not forthcoming from either the Scottish Parliament or Welsh Assembly—the UK Government have tabled a set of amendments to Clause 11 which we will consider later. The Government’s proposals would provide a power to make regulations in certain devolved areas currently subject to EU law, and would prevent the devolved legislatures from taking action in the areas covered by those regulations. Whether noble Lords in this Chamber like it or not, this is regarded by members of all parties in the National Assembly as reflecting a growing approach by the UK Government—namely, in areas where devolution may be a nuisance or a hindrance to the UK Government’s agenda—to roll back devolution, or at the very least to attenuate it, and to centralise certain powers in London. The Welsh and Scottish Governments share this fear. That is why, in the Senedd—thanks largely to the lead of my inspirational colleague Steffan Lewis AM—the Welsh Government have introduced a continuity Bill to safeguard Welsh devolution. That Bill is currently progressing through its legislative steps with all-party support. Assembly Members are taking such a step not as a threat but as a safeguard: they still hope that there may be a meeting of minds between them and Westminster, and I understand they have even drafted a sunset clause which could be triggered if such an agreement were achieved. They look to this Chamber today to take a stand in facilitating that meeting of minds and to ensure that the centralist direction to which they feel they are being subject is brought to an end.</p>
    <p pid="b329.3/5">Alongside the amendments which the UK Government have tabled, they have published a list of 158 areas of intersection of devolved competences with EU law, noting that they envisage regulations temporarily restricting devolved legislatures’ competence—in advance of more substantive arrangements in primary legislation —in up to 24 of those areas. Taking such steps is, rightly or wrongly, widely perceived as a power  grab. These 24 areas, all of which apply to both Wales and Scotland, cover a significant part of devolved responsibilities, including agricultural support, fisheries management, environmental policy, public procurement and food standards. These areas are vital for industries and businesses in Wales, and for the Welsh economy. The amendments would allow the UK Government to make regulations in any or all of these devolved areas.</p>
    <p pid="b329.3/6">I wholeheartedly agree that common frameworks are appropriate in some cases, given the current role of EU law in regulating action in all parts of the UK—</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.330.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.330.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.330.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.330.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.331.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.331.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.331.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.331.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.332.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.332.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.332.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.332.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.332.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.332.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.332.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.332.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.332.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.332.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.333.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.333.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.333.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.333.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.334.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.334.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.335.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.335.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.335.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.335.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.336.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.336.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.336.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.336.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.336.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.336.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.336.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.336.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.336.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.336.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.336.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.336.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.338.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.338.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.338.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.338.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.338.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.338.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.338.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.338.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.338.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.338.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.338.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.338.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.339.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.339.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.339.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.339.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.339.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.339.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.339.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.339.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.339.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.339.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.339.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.339.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.340.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.340.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.340.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.340.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.340.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.340.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.341.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.341.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.341.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.341.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.341.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.341.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.341.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.341.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.341.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.341.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.341.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.341.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.342.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.342.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.342.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.342.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.342.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.342.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.342.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="342" time="17:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b342.2/1">Amendment 282</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.342.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.342.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.342.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.342.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.342.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.342.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.342.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.342.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.343.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.343.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.343.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.343.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="344" time="17:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b344.2/1">Content.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.6" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="344" time="17:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b344.6/1">Content.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.8" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.8" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.9" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.9" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.10" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.10" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.11" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.11" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.12" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.12" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.13" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.13" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.14" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.14" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.344.15" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.344.15" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.345.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.345.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.346.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.346.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.346.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.346.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.346.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.346.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.347.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.347.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.347.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.347.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.347.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.347.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.347.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.347.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.348.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.348.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.348.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.348.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.348.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.348.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.348.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.348.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.348.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.348.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.348.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.348.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.349.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.349.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.349.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.349.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.349.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="349" time="18:13:00" url="">
    <p pid="b349.1/1">Amendment 302A</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.349.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.349.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.350.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.350.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.350.0" speakername="Lord Keen of Elie" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25446" colnum="350" time="18:13:00" url="">
    <p pid="b350.0/1">My Lords, I shall speak also to the other government amendments in this group. We have put forward these amendments to facilitate scrutiny of the Government’s current position on Clause 11. They reflect the status of our discussions with the devolved Administrations, and noble Lords will be aware that our discussions with the Scottish and Welsh Governments are continuing. We remain convinced that this Bill is the right vehicle for providing legal certainty across the UK and that we should reach agreement with the Scottish and Welsh Governments. As such, the Government do not seek a vote on these amendments today and we will withdraw or not move them at the conclusion of the debate, but we will reflect seriously on the points made and incorporate them into our discussions.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/2">The Government have been clear that the Bill is about continuity, certainty and control. That applies equally and without exception to people and businesses across all parts of the United Kingdom. Our approach has always been guided by two principal aims; namely, that we have a fully functioning statute book on exit, and that there are no new barriers to people living and doing business across the United Kingdom. These amendments have been tabled, in line with our commitment made in the other place, to address the concerns raised regarding the current Clause 11. They represent a substantial movement from our original position and reflect the sincerity of our commitment to finding a mutually agreeable position.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/3">We have had lengthy discussions on this issue at official and ministerial level, including at the Joint Ministerial Committee. Noble Lords will well know that the Scottish and Welsh Governments have not yet agreed these amendments, but we will continue to work with them to try and find a way through. I am confident that all parties to this discussion are invested in trying to reach that agreement, as was demonstrated by the constructive tone set at the JMC by the Prime Minister and the First Ministers. This is a crucial piece of legislation in the national interest. It must work for all parts of the United Kingdom and we are sincere in our hope that we will find a way for us all to come together in support of it.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/4">Noble Lords spoke at length at Second Reading and in previous debates of the importance of the “presumption of devolution” and have debated the principle that if there is not a good reason for a matter to be held in common, it should be devolved. That is what these amendments aim to deliver. They would take the existing Clause 11 and effectively turn it on its head. Their effect is that by default on exit day any decision-making powers currently held by the EU in areas that are otherwise devolved would pass directly to our devolved institutions without first being diverted through Westminster. The amendments then give UK Ministers powers to apply targeted and temporary limitations on competence to modify retained EU law, which would in essence have the effect of maintaining existing UK frameworks. We envisage that they will be used in those specific areas where we have identified that a future framework for the United Kingdom may be needed. That would ensure that in those areas the current common approaches established by EU law will continue to apply until we—the United Kingdom Government and the devolved Administrations—can together determine the form that the new bespoke UK framework will take, if one is ultimately required for the benefit of both our communities and our businesses.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/5">I should be clear that the limits that would be applied by these powers are not new limits or constraints. They would merely preserve existing competence in relation to EU law after exit as it stood in relation to EU law immediately prior to exit. Therefore any decision that the devolved institutions could take before exit day will continue to be a decision that they can take after exit day in areas where they have exercised their powers. There is no encroachment into existing devolved areas, and of course in areas where we have not exercised these powers there will be an immediate and significant increase in the decision-making powers of the devolved institutions upon exit. I should also be clear that these limits apply to an area only to the extent it is covered by EU law and not to the entire subject matter. They will not limit competence to make any provision in relation to a subject matter where this does not involve the modification of retained EU law. I urge noble Lords to refer to the Government’s frameworks analysis, published on <phrase class="date" code="2018-03-09">9 March</phrase>, to see the kind of areas where we envisage that the temporary powers may need to be exercised.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/6">Noble Lords will also want to be aware of the additional limits placed on the exercise of these powers. Not only would the powers be subject to the affirmative  procedure but the amendments also apply a reporting duty, a duty to consult the devolved Administrations and a duty to produce explanatory statements.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/7">Ministers will be under a duty to report at regular intervals on the steps taken to implement future frameworks; the way in which the framework principles that underpin that work are applied; steps taken to apply or remove restrictions on devolved competence under the powers; the progress towards removing restrictions and repealing those powers altogether once they have served their purpose; and any other information they deem relevant. All this serves to demonstrate that this mechanism is a temporary means to achieve our end state on frameworks.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/8">Before laying an instrument under these powers, UK Ministers will also be required to consult the relevant devolved Administrations and make a statement on the effect of the instrument and any representations made by the devolved Administrations in response to consultation. Further, since these limits are but a temporary means to preserve existing EU frameworks until they are replaced by a UK framework, the amendments also provide a power to repeal the constraining powers so that they will not be retained for longer than is necessary. Ministers would be under a duty to consider periodically whether it is appropriate to repeal the powers. In doing so, they would be required to have regard to the intended temporary nature of these arrangements and to any progress in putting lasting arrangements in place.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/9">Through this, we have sought to emphasise that these powers and restrictions are not to exist in perpetuity or as a permanent feature of the devolution arrangements. Rather, they provide a short-term fix for our longer, more detailed work on the development of long-term future common arrangements. I note in relation to this the amendments in the name of the noble and learned Lord, Lord Wallace, which would subject the current Clause 11 and any regulations made under the new Clause 11 power relating to Scottish legislative competence to a sunset limit. I understand why that suggestion has been put forward; we have of course been clear that these are temporary arrangements and I am interested to hear the debate on this point.</p>
    <p pid="b350.0/10">I must be clear that the temporary nature of the constraints is not the same as proceeding to a fixed timetable. We need to ensure that these complex matters are given due consideration, and there is a risk that the creation of a sunset merely prolongs the cliff edge.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.352.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.352.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.352.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="352" time="18:13:00" url="">
    <p pid="b352.0/1">Oh!</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.352.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.352.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.352.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.352.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.354.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.354.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.354.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="354" time="18:13:00" url="">
    <p pid="b354.0/1">Amendment 302B (to Amendment 302A)</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.354.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.354.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.354.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.354.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.356.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.356.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.357.8" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.357.8" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.358.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.358.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.358.0" speakername="Lord Mackay of Clashfern" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13122" colnum="358" time="18:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b358.0/1">My Lords, my Amendment 318A is in this group. As your Lordships know, I am a lawyer, but I have already got limited support from the noble Lord, Lord Wigley, who has repeatedly explained that he does not suffer from this disadvantage—I will do my best to take him along with me.</p>
    <p pid="b358.0/2">As I have indicated, I was first introduced to this matter in a discussion with a very distinguished SNP Member in the other place, when we were travelling together from the north. I mentioned to him that I had had no briefing of any sort from the Scottish Government. The next day I got a message from the Scottish Government to say that the Lord Advocate and Mr Russell, the Minister, were very willing to speak to me. I was able to speak to the Lord Advocate that afternoon and to Mr Russell in the early afternoon that Wednesday. I was very emphatically assured by Mr Russell that the Scottish Government were keen to reach an agreement. I am quite satisfied that there is no indication in the attitude of the Scottish Government that this is an attempt to further their ultimate political aim, and that they are seeking to solve this matter in a way that accords with the dignity of the Scottish Government. I said that I did not want to do or say anything that would impede agreement, and I now hope to show how agreement can be reached.</p>
    <p pid="b358.0/3">Before I explain the amendment, I will say a word or two about the law that lies behind it—I will take Scotland as an example, as the other Administrations have similar provisions. The devolution settlement in the Scotland Act is subject to EU law. That considerably restricts what the Scottish Administration can do at present, but when Brexit comes along that limitation will disappear. Included in those limitations are the legislative powers of Brussels to legislate in the United Kingdom. From one point of view, it is wise to analyse these powers in this way: a power that can be made effective within a single area of legislative competence in the United Kingdom should go straight to that level—in other words, to the devolved Administration. That is, if the power does not require more than one of our legislative areas in order to be effective, it should go straight to the devolved Administration.</p>
    <p pid="b358.0/4">But there are EU powers which can only be effective when they cover more than one of our legislative areas. The one that is of most relevance in this connection is that which provides for the single market. As your Lordships know, and as the Scottish Government certainly know, the single market is quite an important feature of the present negotiations. Part of that single market is the single market in the United Kingdom. It is 100% obvious that, if you are going to legislate for the single market in the United Kingdom, it is legislation that affects all of the countries within the United Kingdom and the legislatures that support them. Therefore, it is absolutely plain that the ultimate power to settle the single market provisions lies with the United Kingdom Parliament.</p>
    <p pid="b358.0/5">But—and this is an important consideration—it is extremely wise to proceed by agreement where it is at all possible. A good deal of agreement has already been reached. As I said, I was assured by Mr Russell when I first spoke to him—and again when he later saw my amendment, which he welcomed subject to qualifications such as the noble Lord, Lord Wigley, will propose—that the Scottish Government are very anxious to reach agreement.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.359.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.359.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.359.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.359.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.361.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.361.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.362.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.362.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.362.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.362.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.362.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.362.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.363.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.363.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.363.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.363.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.363.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.363.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.363.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.363.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.363.3" speakername="Lord Grabiner" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13568" colnum="363" time="19:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b363.3/1">The amendment includes the proposition that if the panel “consider it necessary”, they may refer the matter to the Supreme Court of the United Kingdom. I am not aware that there is any mechanism that could possibly enable that to happen. Moreover, even if it were possible, I suspect that the court would not be very grateful to receive what essentially would be a highly political rather than a purely legal question. If I may respectfully say so, it is a rather an unrealistic proposal.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.363.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.363.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.364.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.364.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.364.0" speakername="Lord Foulkes of Cumnock" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10211" colnum="364" time="19:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b364.0/1">My Lords, I speak to Amendments 318B, 318C, 318D and 318E, which, it does not take a lot of working out, follow on from Amendment 318 and 318A. In fact, as the noble Lord, Lord Wigley, said, it is interesting that what I suggest in three of those amendments in many ways corresponds exactly with what the noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay, suggested—as amended by the noble Lord, Lord Wigley. Yet we came to the conclusion separately. We may have been inspired by the same people, the same thinking and the same ideas, but we came to draft them separately, which is interesting.</p>
    <p pid="b364.0/2">It is also really helpful that the noble and learned Lord, Lord Keen, has said quite clearly that the Government are willing to look at these amendments and at some way of getting out of the impasse in which they find themselves. That is a really helpful way forward. However, the Government are the architects of their own misfortune. As my noble friend Lord Griffiths of Burry Port said, the Joint Ministerial Committee should have met more frequently and earlier. We were sent just the other day details of the fifth ministerial committee—on <phrase class="date" code="2018-10-16">16 October</phrase>. It is extraordinary that we had only four ministerial committees dealing with this issue before then. It really is a dereliction of duty by the Government, which I think comes from the fact that, within Whitehall—as I found when I was a Minister—there is no understanding about devolution and what it involves. The Minister responsible was perhaps Oliver Letwin or Chris Grayling, so you can understand why they did not understand—but what worries me is that the noble and learned Lord, Lord Keen, has been the Advocate-General for some time, and he should have alerted the people around Whitehall and others to this problem a lot earlier. Indeed, the Secretary of State, David Mundell, who I will concede is a very nice man—</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.364.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.364.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.364.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.364.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.364.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.364.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.364.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.364.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.366.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.366.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.366.0" speakername="Lord Wallace of Tankerness" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13940" colnum="366" time="19:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b366.0/1">My Lords, I shall speak to Amendments 302BA, 312 and 318 in my name, but I shall start by speaking more to the generality by responding to the government amendments moved by the Minister. It is fair to acknowledge that much has happened since Second Reading when I and many others criticised the architecture of the original Clause 11, not least because it showed scant regard for the spirit and structure of the original devolution settlement. It had a system of conferred powers that was totally alien to how devolution had performed and been structured until this point.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/2">However, I give credit to the Government for tabling these amendments. They have thought to recast Clause 11 and the related schedules, and I think it was acknowledged earlier that there is more work to be done. When you get legislation like this and new situations arise, it is amazing how new words come into the vocabulary. The Government have claimed that most of the powers at the so-called intersects will go directly to Cardiff, Edinburgh and Belfast on exit day, subject only to relatively few remaining—they emphasise that this will be temporary, though I shall return to that—to secure the UK single market until such time as that framework is put in place.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/3">As has been acknowledged, that is a welcome step. It shows a lot of progress and, I think, a lot of good will towards seeking an agreement. However, it has clearly not yet been sufficient to allow the Scottish and Welsh Governments to recommend the Legislative Consent Motions to their respective Parliament and Assembly. Indeed, the letter from the First Ministers of Scotland and Wales to the Lord Speaker that was circulated to all Members of your Lordships’ House says:</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/4">“In being asked to give legislative consent to the EU (Withdrawal) Bill on this basis”—</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/5">that is, on the basis of the new amendments—</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/6" class="indent">“the devolved legislatures would be being asked to agree to the creation of this power with no certainty about where frameworks will be established, how these will work, how they will be governed and how we will go from temporary restrictions to longer term solutions”.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/7">It is also arguable that the amendments do not do precisely what the Government claim they are seeking to do. The Government have said—indeed, the Minister has said today—that the intention is that the vast majority of powers identified at the intersects will go directly to the devolved institutions. The noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay of Clashfern, rightly said that that is the proper thing to do. However, if one looks at the amendments before us, while much has been said about a figure of 24, one sees that there is nothing in the Bill that restricts it to 24. Technically, and I think this was a point made by the noble Lord, Lord Griffiths of Burry Port, all 158 could be subject to this freeze and this restriction. They could all be  subject to regulations made under the powers in the revised Clause 11 and there would be no provision for consent from the Scottish or Welsh Ministers, let alone from the Scottish Parliament or the Welsh Assembly.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/8">It would help considerably if, in the body of legislation, it was made clear in some way which powers would go directly, or if there was a schedule concerning which powers would be the subject of framework agreements. I do not doubt for one minute that there will be some negotiation about what should be in frameworks and what should or should not be a UK framework. That is perfectly proper for negotiation. I welcome what the Minister said earlier: agriculture is set out as a broad heading but he accepts that agriculture has to be subdivided and not all aspects of it would be the subject of frameworks. Indeed, it is worth noting that NFU Scotland identifies in a briefing paper animal welfare and traceability, public health, pesticides, regulation and food labelling as examples of overarching areas of regulation that would be best suited to being managed on a commonly agreed framework basis. There is lots of scope for talking to stakeholders about what the framework should be, but it would be very helpful if that could be in the Bill.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/9">I do not underestimate for one moment that there will be work to do, but we should perhaps reflect that it will be at least four weeks until we come to deal with these issues on Report. It is worth reminding ourselves that the House of Commons Select Committee on Scottish Affairs recommended back in November that there should be clarity on this before the Bill reached Third Reading in the House of Commons. I do not take away from the work that has been done by officials, but if there is a will to get there, I am sure it could be done.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/10">One other reflection on this point is that earlier today, in response to an intervention from me, the noble and learned Lord said that, given that we are now to have a transition period, we will have to accommodate that transition period in future legislation, a withdrawal and implementation Bill, so we may not need these frameworks until <phrase class="date" code="2018-12-31">31 December</phrase> 2020 or <phrase class="date" code="2018-01-01">1 January</phrase> 2021, which provides further time to sort out what should be in later legislation. But I would rather strike while the iron is hot and seek what can be done in this Bill.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/11">It has also been said that these measures are temporary. The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster went out of his way to emphasise that in the letter that he sent to all Peers. The Government have, to their credit, included several extra provisions to buttress their position that they should be temporary by reporting requirements, and these are all welcome, but, unlike some other parts of the Bill, there is no sunset clause. That is why, in Amendment 312, which was tabled before the new amendments, my noble friend Lord Thomas of Gresford and I recommended that there should be a sunset on the whole power after two years and, in Amendment 302BA, I suggest that any regulations brought forward under the new powers should themselves lapse after two years. The noble Lord, Lord Foulkes of Cumnock, said that it should be five years. We could have a debate about that but, again, the principle is trying to build confidence to get an agreement between the  Scottish and Welsh Governments and the UK Government, and to have a sunset clause would go a considerable way to help that.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/12">As we have heard in the previous three contributions, there could be dispute about the frameworks. Our Amendment 318 would put the Joint Ministerial Committee on European negotiations on a statutory footing. In October 2016, to much fanfare, we were told that this new committee had been set up,</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/13" class="indent">“to ensure that the interests of all parts of the United Kingdom are protected and advanced, and to develop a UK approach and objectives for the forthcoming negotiations”.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/14">That has probably been more honoured in the breach than it has in practice. We know that in recent weeks there have been more concerted efforts in the committee to try to gain agreement on what we are discussing tonight, but there might be a lot of advantage in putting it on a statutory basis so that there could not be any backsliding on when it meets, as has happened before.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/15">I welcome the initiative taken by the noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay of Clashfern, and the amendments proposed by the noble Lord, Lord Wigley and Lord Foulkes of Cumnock, because they constructively try to address how we resolve some of the difficulties. There clearly are difficulties and differences, and we must try to start thinking outside the box and creatively. The noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay of Clashfern, picks up very well one difficulty: the United Kingdom Parliament is also the Parliament for England—England does not have a separate legislature, as Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland do.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/16">I was reminded of my colleague Mr Ross Finnie, Minister for the Environment and Rural Development in the first Scottish Administration. His experience of meeting counterparts from Wales, Northern Ireland and Defra was that some Secretaries of State saw their role as to be the UK chair of the meetings, with the English Minister of State arguing England’s case, whereas other Secretaries of State could not see the difference between an English position and a UK position. He said that, clearly, they made far more progress when they had a Secretary of State who saw him or herself as holding the ring as the UK Minister with an English Minister of State arguing the English position.</p>
    <p pid="b366.0/17">We must recognise that, as the noble Lord, Lord Foulkes, said, it is asymmetrical.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.368.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.368.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.369.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.369.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.370.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.370.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.370.0" speakername="Lord McConnell of Glenscorrodale" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/14049" colnum="370" time="19:30:00" url="">
    <p pid="b370.0/1">My Lords, I have been very critical of the way that both the Government and the Scottish Government have conducted these discussions over the past 12 months, but I want to start by being very positive in your Lordships’ House this evening. I think the Government have moved considerably; I think the reversal of the principle behind the new clause is very welcome indeed; and I think it is now very likely that we are close to an agreement on the different categories of responsibility and competence in the different sections. I very much welcome the assurances from the Minister in the earlier debate that legislative consent Motions will be required for any primary legislation that would enact these new frameworks. I also welcome the tone of the debate tonight and the fact that the Minister is welcoming the different amendments that have been put forward and the ideas that have been suggested and is willing to look at them with his team over the coming weeks, before we get to the stage of having to vote on any specific proposals.</p>
    <p pid="b370.0/2">However, I want to make one specific point, in the interests of brevity and concentrating on what I think  is most important here this evening. The way in which these frameworks are established is perhaps critical to getting the agreement to get to the stage of the frameworks in the first place. Whatever opinions each of us might have about the taking back of control to the UK from the European Union, in that exercise of taking back control to the UK I think the Government could be much more ambitious in setting out a new way of working inside the United Kingdom. Frankly, the joint ministerial committees have never worked, from the very first year. They were chaired by UK Ministers; they were sometimes consultation exercises; they were more often a brief, cursory discussion around a table. They were very occasionally brought together to reach agreement on a specific item, but those agreements were always much better reached in other forums or bilaterally. Tony Blair and I both tried to get rid of them. We did not succeed, but I wish that we had.</p>
    <p pid="b370.0/3">The Government need to think way beyond the joint ministerial committees. Perhaps the noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay of Clashfern, has started to point us in the right direction for a way in which we can build a new relationship among the four Governments. What we need to look at is not a joint ministerial committee but a new form of ministerial council within the United Kingdom that might perhaps have a rotating chair, rather than being chaired by the UK Secretary of State, and that would have some sort of procedure for resolving disputes. It obviously could not use qualified majority voting, and it might or might not have a veto, but at least each case would be agreed properly among the different sets of Governments. If the Government could do some radical thinking on this over the next few weeks, before we get to the stage of finally voting on this Bill and agreeing the way ahead on frameworks, then I think they would be on much firmer ground to get agreement on the individual competencies and then to get consent. Although not necessarily required legally or constitutionally, it would be better for the United Kingdom if consent is acquired for this Bill and for the subsequent actions that will take us forward to the next steps. I urge the Government to think more ambitiously about the way these frameworks will look in the future, while I welcome the steps that have already been taken to put in place restricted time scales, which might yet include a sunset clause—that might be very wise—to be clear about the reversal of the principle; to devolve things unless they have to be reserved; and to be willing, tonight, to listen to all the amendments.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.371.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.371.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.371.0" speakername="Lord Lang of Monkton" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13382" colnum="371" time="19:30:00" url="">
    <p pid="b371.0/1">My Lords, after roaming around the various amendments to the government amendment, I would like to steer us back to the government amendment itself, which I support and which I hope will form a pathway to getting this matter resolved. I am afraid my remarks will be mainly focused on Scotland, where the battle has been fiercest, but I will refer to the other devolved Administrations in the context of the generality.</p>
    <p pid="b371.0/2">We have got here by a tortuous route of JMC meetings, consultations, arguments and a lot of delay. I acknowledge the willingness of the Government, in particular, to try to follow this approach of constantly  being willing to participate in discussions and consultations. Much reference has been made in earlier debates to the spirit of devolution, to which the intergovernmental relations paper published by the Constitution Committee some time ago referred—indeed, we argued for many things, including some just referred to by the noble Lord, Lord McConnell. Given where we are in this farrago of committee meetings and consultations and rebuffs and demands and arguments about “consent” and “consult”, it is a relief to have an amendment to the Bill around which we can debate and, I hope, remove the deadlock.</p>
    <p pid="b371.0/3">I prefer to start by reference to a component of the debate that seems to have been notable by its absence in discussion until my noble and learned friend Lord Keen raised it in the last debate, namely the Sewel convention. When the Scottish Act of 1978 was going through Parliament, I asked my lamented and good friend Lord MacKay of Ardbrecknish what it was all about. It was not called the Sewel convention at that stage. He said, “Oh, it’s a good-will measure. When we and the Scottish Government both want to legislate on the same subject, we’ll offer to do it for them to avoid duplication”. If only. The spirit of devolution may have been alive then, but it has taken a battering since. The finished version has turned out a bit differently. Far from being a good-will gesture to foster harmonious relations, it has become a battleground on which Parliament seems under constant challenge, with one visit already to the Supreme Court and another allegedly brewing. That is not the spirit of devolution.</p>
    <p pid="b371.0/4">The Government deserve credit for endless trust and courtesy, but their patience has gone unrewarded. It seems that they are left with no alternative but to act as they now propose. The noble Lord, Lord Thomas of Gresford, who I am glad to see in his place, said in an earlier debate that it is a pity that devolution has got tangled up with the Brexit Bill. I absolutely agree with him—I wish they could have been taken separately—but it obviously is not possible. We are where we are. In the much larger arena of the Brexit negotiations, the challenge of this Bill is full of difficulties and complex issues. No solution is easy, but the Government have to make progress to keep to the timetable. In that context, I think reference to the Sewel convention makes clear that Parliament can legislate on devolved matters. That is an important point to remember and one that could have been prayed upon at the very outset as an alternative route to securing a satisfactory conclusion. Of course it is not something to do lightly, but we in the devolved Administrations need a solution. The word “normally” offers a key to this. There can surely be nothing less normal in the world of law-making than legislation to retrieve to our shores from the European Union over 40 years of legislative activity against a tight deadline and in advance of the moment of transfer—a retrieval that is vital to the maintenance of the rule of law as Brexit takes place. If that is not abnormal as an event, I do not know what is.</p>
    <p pid="b371.0/5">The Scotland Act and the Wales Act, as amended, and the convention are the nearest we can get to a stable base on which the devolution settlements can have some hope of harmonious survival, provided all parties respect that base. Enoch Powell’s dictum that power devolved is power retained has to prevail or the  centre cannot hold, but sovereignty can be courteously delivered and received. The Government’s record on that is good. The Bill respects it and the guarantees that the Government have given. It specifically guarantees that no existing devolved power will be changed. Everything already devolved stays devolved. The area of dispute is a narrow, temporary and reducing one. As the Government’s amendment concerning EU powers being brought into the UK for the first time demonstrates—under the EU treaties, those powers must be transferred to the nation state in the first instance—the vast majority will go straight through to the devolved Administrations. Only those powers temporarily reserved that affect national frameworks, on which the devolved Administrations reached agreement in principle as long ago as last October, will be frozen en route until the frameworks can be decided upon. My noble and learned friend the Advocate-General covered that matter very effectively in his speech in the previous debate.</p>
    <p pid="b371.0/6">I respect the principles advanced by noble Lords and their sensitivity over matters that they point out are devolved, but there are other factors that again, in the spirit of devolution, could be deemed worthy of some movement by the devolved Administrations. These competencies and my noble and learned friend’s speech were very helpful on this—indeed, it makes my own speech almost redundant from now on, but I will make it anyway. These competencies coming home from the European Union were not ours to devolve before and do not necessarily fit in under the headings of what is claimed as devolved. They were not ours to devolve before; they are in many ways new and additional and reflect the changed legislative priorities that have evolved over the past 40 years. I just give one simple example of that change in agriculture: 40 years ago, we had a Ministry of Agriculture; now we have a Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs—a very much changed animal. Virtually all these new powers will as soon as possible end up with the devolved Administrations.</p>
    <p pid="b371.0/7">I do not know how the Government could do more without jeopardising its obligations to the United Kingdom as a whole. This Parliament is the only one that can negotiate the Brexit deal—the outcome will after all form part of an international treaty—and this Parliament is the Parliament of Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland, as well as of England and the United Kingdom. I sometimes think that Scotland’s First Minister occasionally forgets that the Prime Minister is also her Prime Minister and that the Westminster Government—as the SNP derisively refers to us, as though we were a foreign power—are also Scotland’s Government as well as that of the other parts of the UK. It is the Prime Minister who can protect the First Minister from herself by ensuring that Scotland remains in the UK, as its people decided only three years ago, and thus in the United Kingdom’s single market, which is the mainstay of Scotland’s economy. As I think all your Lordships now know, it takes four and half times more exports than the entire European Union does.</p>
    <p pid="b371.0/8">Yet still they rage against the light. The intransigence shown by the Scottish Administration was always likely to emerge. I diverge here from my noble and  learned friend Lord Mackay of Clashfern—though fortunately not on a legal point—as I believe it was always going to emerge, and it is what the Scottish Government mean by “negotiation”, because they are working to a different agenda, an agenda with only one item on it: independence. Everything in every area of government in Scotland is subservient to that, hence the neglect that we see of education, the economy and all the other matters that are their responsibility. If they can find of way of turning everything that happens into a source of grievance, they will do so. Grievance is their default position. They would make a grievance out of a ray of sunshine if they thought it would help their cause. Where in that Administration is the spirit of devolution? There is no power grab in the measures proposed in the government amendment, quite the reverse; it is a power bonanza. The devolved Administrations should welcome it as a ray of sunshine.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.374.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.374.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.374.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.374.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.374.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.374.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.374.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.374.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.374.3" speakername="Lord Lang of Monkton" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13382" colnum="374" time="19:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b374.3/1">My Lords, I too regret having to refer to the behaviour of the Scottish National Party and its constant attempts to find issues on which it can exercise grievance, but that is what is happening. It is because of that attitude that we are where we are now and that the consultations that were allegedly going extremely well throughout the earlier months have run up against a time limit. We are blinding  ourselves to reality if we do not take account of the fact that the Scottish Administration has a completely different agenda from this one—notwithstanding the bonhomie of Mr Russell, which my noble and learned friend Lord Mackay of Clashfern was fortunate enough to encounter. I regret having to say it, but it has to be said, otherwise we are blinding ourselves to reality.</p>
    <p pid="b374.3/2">I do not dismiss the Government’s past willingness to consult patiently and, again, I respect their willingness to withdraw this amendment so that it can be further debated and discussed. That is entirely in line with the path that they have pursued, which is creditable and desirable. How I wish the other participants in these discussions could unanimously take the same approach. It is a tribute to the constitutional proprieties that we all like to see, seeking as the Government did to negotiate in good faith, to find a route that would not require them to assert the sovereignty of this Parliament. But it did not work in this context and I do not think it was ever going to work. In the end, the supremacy of the union must come first, as another Constitution Committee report, The Union and Devolution, recently suggested.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.375.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.375.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.375.0" speakername="Lord Beith" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10034" colnum="375" time="19:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b375.0/1">My Lords, the noble Lord is a former chairman of the Constitution Committee, but he is perhaps doing a disservice to its present members by not reflecting that the committee felt that progress had to be made in this area, not least because the Parliaments in both Edinburgh and Cardiff, across the parties, were unhappy with the Government’s original proposals.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.375.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.375.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.375.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.375.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.375.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.375.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.376.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.376.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.376.0" speakername="Lord Campbell of Pittenweem" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10088" colnum="376" time="19:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b376.0/1">I shall speak briefly to the amendment proposed by the noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay of Clashfern. I do not do so because I once enjoyed the privilege of being one of his deputes when he was Lord Advocate for Scotland—as did the noble and learned Lords, Lord Hope and Lord Cullen, both of whom are in their places this evening. I do so without detracting in any way from the amendment in the name of my noble and learned friend Lord Wallace of Tankerness. What attracts me to the amendment proposed by the noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay, is its simplicity and practicality. It is easily understood, and coming, as it were, from a Scottish source, it pays due regard to economy. For those reasons it is well worthy of consideration. Its simplicity makes it easily capable of being understood not just by those who will have responsibilities under it, but by members of the public.</p>
    <p pid="b376.0/2">It is for those reasons that I am, with due deference, rather doubtful about the amendment tabled by the noble Lord, Lord Wigley. The problem with it is that, apart from the reference to the Supreme Court turning into some kind of court of arbitration, and I know of no process or procedure that would allow for that—</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.376.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.376.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.376.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.376.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.376.2" speakername="Lord Campbell of Pittenweem" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10088" colnum="376" time="19:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b376.2/1">The noble and learned Lord’s intervention is most helpful. Of course, the language of proposed subsection (17), in Amendment 318AA,</p>
    <p pid="b376.2/2" class="indent">“refer any question to the Supreme Court”,</p>
    <p pid="b376.2/3">supports the view that the use of the Supreme Court in such circumstances would be, to put it mildly, doubtful.</p>
    <p pid="b376.2/4">My difficulty with the proposal of the noble Lord, Lord Wigley, is that it is bound to encourage delay. His amendment says:</p>
    <p pid="b376.2/5">“The Panel may call witnesses or take legal advice”.</p>
    <p pid="b376.2/6">If witnesses are called they may have to be cross-examined, and if there is to be cross-examination there may have to be representation by counsel, or something of that kind. It is not difficult to imagine what is proposed in the amendment turning into something of a full-blown hearing, rather like, for example, industrial tribunals.</p>
    <p pid="b376.2/7">Under suggested subsection (15)(a), regard must be had to whether something,</p>
    <p pid="b376.2/8" class="indent">“is reasonable, in all the circumstances”.</p>
    <p pid="b376.2/9">As soon as the concept of reasonableness appears in a statute, it opens up the possibility of judicial review. Even if it were not to be granted, none the less an application for judicial review could obviously, and unfortunately, delay the outcome of a decision that might be of considerable economic as well as political importance. For those reasons, however well intentioned the noble Lord’s proposal is, I do not think it stands any proper comparison with that of the noble and learned Lord, Lord Mackay. I therefore urge the Government to give serious consideration to that, for the reasons the noble and learned Lord set out, which I have tried to follow.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.377.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.377.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.377.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.377.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.377.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.377.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.378.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.378.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.378.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.378.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.378.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="378" time="19:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b378.1/1">Oh!</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.378.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.378.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.378.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.378.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.378.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.378.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.379.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.379.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.379.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.379.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.380.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.380.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.380.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.380.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.380.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.380.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.380.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.380.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.381.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.381.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.381.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.381.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.381.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.381.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.381.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.381.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.382.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.382.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.382.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="382" time="20:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b382.0/1">Oh!</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.382.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.382.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.382.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.382.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.384.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.384.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.385.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.385.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.385.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.385.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.387.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.386.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.387.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.386.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.389.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.388.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.390.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.389.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.390.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.389.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.391.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.390.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.391.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.390.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.391.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.390.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.392.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.391.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.392.0" speakername="Lord Hain" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10252" colnum="392" time="20:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b392.0/1">I completely agree with my noble friend; he spelt it out very clearly.</p>
    <p pid="b392.0/2">At the same time, this approach would provide transparency about the areas in which devolved competence would be affected, which is sadly lacking in the approach embodied, until now at least, in the Government’s amendments. It would also enable the Scottish Parliament and the Assembly to agree to the list of retained powers—reinforcing my noble friend’s point—through the very act of providing legislative consent to the Bill. Such an approach would thus reassure the devolved institutions that the regulation-making power proposed by the Government could not be used to specify areas of retained EU law not requiring frameworks. That is a very important point.</p>
    <p pid="b392.0/3">If the schedule idea is potentially a magic bullet, why might the Government resist it? I am informed that the first argument is that it cannot be done in time for Report. I am not sure that I buy this argument; Report does not take place until well after Easter, which is many weeks away. We are told that significant work has been done on potential framework areas and the list published recently by the Government—though not agreed with the devolved Administrations, I understand—comes fairly close to defining legally which current EU law restrictions may need to be continued while frameworks are negotiated. Surely if the Government need to specify these areas in regulations, they will need to do so sooner rather than later in any event.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.392.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.391.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.392.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.391.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.393.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.392.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.394.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.393.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.394.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.393.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.394.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.393.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.394.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.393.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.394.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.393.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.395.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.394.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.397.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.396.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.398.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.397.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.399.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.398.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.399.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.398.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.399.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.398.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.399.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.398.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.402.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.401.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.402.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="402" time="21:15:00" url="">
    <p pid="b402.0/1">Minister.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.402.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.401.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.405.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.404.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21b.406.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2018-03-21c.404.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

