<publicwhip scraperversion="a" latest="yes">
  <major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2019-12-18a.5.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="5" time="14:30:00" url="">
Deaths of a Member and Former Members
</major-heading>
  <speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2019-12-18a.5.1" speakername="Lord Fowler" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10212" colnum="5" time="14:36:00" url="">
    <p pid="a5.1/1">My Lords, I regret to inform the House of the deaths of the noble Lord, Lord Mawhinney, on <phrase class="date" code="2019-11-09">9 November</phrase>; the noble and gallant Lord, Lord Bramall, on <phrase class="date" code="2019-11-12">12 November</phrase>; and the noble Lord, Lord Feldman, on <phrase class="date" code="2019-11-19">19 November</phrase>. On behalf of the House, I extend our condolences to their families and friends.</p>
  </speech>
  <major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2019-12-18a.6.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="6" time="14:36:00" url="">
Retirements of Members
</major-heading>
  <speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2019-12-18a.6.1" speakername="Lord Fowler" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10212" colnum="6" time="14:37:00" url="">
    <p pid="a6.1/1">My Lords, I should also like to notify the House of the retirements with effect from <phrase class="date" code="2019-11-28">28 November</phrase> of the noble Earl, Lord Crawford and Balcarres, and with effect from <phrase class="date" code="2019-12-17">17 December</phrase> of the noble Lord, Lord Wright of Richmond, pursuant to Section 1 of the House of Lords Reform Act 2014. On behalf of the House, I should like to thank the noble Earl and the noble Lord for their very much-valued service to this House.</p>
  </speech>
  <major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2019-12-18a.6.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="6" time="14:37:00" url="">
Oaths and Affirmations
</major-heading>
  <speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2019-12-18a.6.3" speakername="Lord Fowler" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10212" colnum="6" time="14:38:00" url="">
    <p pid="a6.3/1">My Lords, as I can see you are waiting, we will now continue the process of taking the oath and affirming. I remind Members of the House that it has been agreed to give priority to Members with disability or impaired mobility.</p>
    <p pid="a6.3/2">Several noble Lords took the oath or made the solemn affirmation, and signed an undertaking to abide by the Code of Conduct.</p>
    <p pid="a6.3/3" class="italic">House adjourned at 7.30 pm.</p>
  </speech>
</publicwhip>
