<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="/home/twfy-live/parldata/scrapedxml/lordspages/daylord2022-05-11a.xml" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.8" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.8" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.23.9" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.23.9" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.24.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.24.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.24.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.24.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.25.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.25.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.25.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.25.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.25.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.25.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.25.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.25.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.26.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.26.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.26.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.26.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.26.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.26.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.26.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.26.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.26.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.26.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.26.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.26.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.26.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.26.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.26.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.26.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.27.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.27.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.27.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.27.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.27.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.27.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.27.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.27.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.27.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.27.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.27.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.27.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.27.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.27.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.27.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.27.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.28.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.28.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.28.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.28.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.28.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.28.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.29.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.29.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.29.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.29.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.29.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.29.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.29.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.29.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.32.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.32.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.32.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.32.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.32.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.32.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.35.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.35.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.37.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.37.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.39.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.39.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.40.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.40.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.42.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.42.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.43.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.43.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.45.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.45.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.47.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.47.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.48.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.48.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.50.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.50.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.52.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.52.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.53.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.53.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.56.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.56.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.58.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.58.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.59.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.59.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.61.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.61.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.63.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.63.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.65.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.65.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.66.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.66.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.69.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.69.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.69.0" speakername="Baroness Bottomley of Nettlestone" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10058" colnum="69" time="18:11:00" url="">
    <p pid="a69.0/1">My Lords, it is always a joy to follow my noble friend Lord Inglewood, who was without doubt one of my favourite, most capable and competent Ministers when I was in government. I could simply put my feet up and he would cover all the most complex and difficult topics. We have heard today again a thoughtful speech from him, covering in detail a great number of areas.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/2">Before referring to the right reverend Prelate, I wanted to mention in passing my noble friends Lord Sherbourne of Didsbury and Lady Fraser of Craigmaddie, who made wonderful speeches yesterday in moving and seconding the Motion for the humble Address. To me, that is the most difficult thing that any of us are ever asked to do in this House, and I congratulate them on it. Just as a reflection of life in the House of Lords, my noble friend Lord Sherbourne was my contemporary, friend and ally in all those years when I worked with Margaret Thatcher. My noble friend Lady Fraser, a highly regarded and excellent woman, was a contemporary of my daughter when she was at Cambridge—so the generations move on.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/3">The right reverend Prelate has been Bishop of Guildford for a long time. Every time I saw him, I would say, “When are you coming to the House of Lords?” I was worried that he might die before he arrived—but I am absolutely delighted to see him. I already know from his work in the diocese what a wonderful person he is, and what wonderful spiritual and practical leadership he displays. I was a lay canon for many years at the cathedral before the right reverend Prelate arrived, although there is no connection. But this must be the culmination of his aspirations. As a Lord spiritual, he  is of course involved in theology but also in the law—and it will not be beyond the wit of Peers in this noble House to think of ways in which the bassoon can be played and put to good effect on many occasions. I think we will be queueing for tickets.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/4">When the right reverend Prelate spoke, he reminded me of why the Lords spiritual nearly always bring a particular contribution. They have served in both very prosperous and very poor areas. Long ago, it used to be the case that MPs served a form of apprenticeship; a Labour MP was a candidate in a very prosperous constituency, lost and then went to a safer seat, which was likely to be a more impoverished one. By contrast, a Conservative MP would serve their apprenticeship by starting in a poor area before then moving to a more prosperous one. What that meant was that we had individuals in the House who really understood about deprivation and disadvantage as well as prosperity and wealth. The right reverend Prelate said that there were food banks in Farnham, and I would entirely endorse that view—that the poverty and deprivation in a prosperous area can be as acute, or even more acute and painful, as in an area where there are many people on the free school list.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/5">In my own case, I have had that exact story. I am a one-nation Tory. I believe in levelling-up, like my noble friend, and have spent many years working with the noble Baronesses, Lady Meacher and Lady Lister, and the noble Lord, Lord Field, at the Child Poverty Action Group, and then in Bethnal Green, Peckham and Brixton, before becoming the Member of Parliament for a very prosperous area, South West Surrey. When I left the Commons, my aim was to reconnect with that part of my own agenda, which I mind about. I agreed to become chancellor of the University of Hull 16 years ago. I was subsequently asked to be sheriff of the city of Kingston upon Hull by the very excellent Labour leader there—who just lost—and since then I have been seriously engaged in what we can do practically to reduce the gaps.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/6">The noble Lord, Lord Kakkar, talked about health inequalities. In Hull, there is a major medical school which has had further investment and expansion, because if you train doctors in London, they want to stay in London, and if you train doctors in Hull, the chances are that they will stay in Hull, and the burden of morbidity and mortality in that part of the world is very great. The figure that the noble Lord used I use frequently: the seven-year gap between life expectancy in the Humber region and in prosperous areas of Surrey. The training of doctors, nurses, and other professions aligned to medicine of course creates jobs, but it also creates long-term investment which I hope will reduce inequalities.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/7">In her excellent opening comments, my noble friend the Minister talked about enshrining in law the 12 levelling- up missions outlined in the White Paper and giving the Government a duty to report annually until 2030. I am a strong advocate for the government White Paper. This is like a PhD thesis. I congratulate not only the Secretary of State but Andy Haldane, the chief economist at the Bank of England, who has had a major input. The detail, the analysis and the papers involved are formidable. Credit should also go to an earlier Levelling-up Minister, the noble Lord, Lord O'Neill, he of the  northern powerhouse. He had a lot of intellectual heft and thought invested in this. If you ask him what he thinks about the White Paper, he will say that it is about measuring the outcomes: it is the KPIs, it is the targets, it is making sure that we hold the Government’s feet to the fire, and all our feet to the fire. As my noble friend said, it is not a wish list; it has to be an action programme.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/8">The noble Lord, Lord O’Neill, said that the real issue is that levelling-up and devolution provide true accountability. The crucial ingredient now is full, unequivocal business engagement and commitment. We need a locally driven passion to do things differently, with a surge of private sector investment to seize those opportunities. That must be right and is very much what the noble Baroness, Lady Valentine, said. I know her work and have shared much of it at London First business community and elsewhere. She referred to the city of culture bid in Bradford; that in Hull was the most wonderful boost and catalyst for opportunity, employment, and well-being.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/9">I am delighted to say that in the White Paper Hull is mentioned as a private sector-led partnership. It says that the Hull economy has great potential and that:</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/10" class="indent">“Recent government announcements and initiatives such as the Humber Freeport and Net Zero, coupled with private sector investment, provide the opportunity and catalyst for the region to realise its potential. The Humber is playing a key role in energy. Through its natural geography and emerging cluster, the Humber will help to ensure that offshore wind, industrial decarbonisation, carbon capture, and other technologies will sustain key industries and create high quality jobs at scale for years to come.”</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/11">I must pay tribute to the university for being such a catalyst for change by providing the evidence, the innovation and a business centre. But the real point is that in Hull they have created Opportunity Humber, which has already met and which is led by the chief executive of Reckitt, Laxman Narasimhan. There are people from Siemens Gamesa, ABP, Drax, National Grid Ventures, Ørsted, Equinor and Phillips 66 on the board of that body, along with the four local councils. It is about having local and global businesses putting in the investment and care that they have. Arup has prepared a first-rate report in detail on what needs to be done.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/12">I recognise the huge difficulties of the time in which we live. We have war and inflation; we have the consequences of Covid and much else. However, this levelling-up agenda is one that resonates and which I believe we will deliver. In the foreword to the levelling-up White Paper, the Prime Minister said it was:</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/13" class="indent">“A vision for the future that will see public spending on R&amp;D increased in every part of the country; transport connectivity reaching London-like levels within and between all our towns and cities; faster broadband in every community; life expectancies rising; violent crime falling; schools improving; and private sector investment unleashed”.</p>
    <p pid="a69.0/14">That is the economic, social and political challenge of our time. These are great words but I believe that with the White Paper and the measures in the Queen’s Speech, we can deliver those targets with real commitment and engagement with the community and business by 2030.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.71.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.71.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.74.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.74.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.76.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.76.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.78.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.78.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.79.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.79.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.81.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.81.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.83.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.83.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.83.0" speakername="Lord Truscott" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/12845" colnum="83" time="19:09:00" url="">
    <p pid="a83.0/1">I commend the right reverend Prelate the Bishop of Guildford on his excellent and thoughtful speech.</p>
    <p pid="a83.0/2">I am very disappointed that the proposed renters reform Bill and the second stage of leasehold reform were not directly mentioned in the gracious Speech. In saying this, I declare an interest as a long-standing leaseholder and landlord. As the Minister said earlier in the debate, a renters reform Bill will nevertheless be brought forward in the current parliamentary Session, although the second stage of leasehold reform will seemingly not, despite talk of it being dealt with in the next parliamentary Session.</p>
    <p pid="a83.0/3">I hope that the leasehold reform Bill will not be kicked into the long grass and effectively dropped. I ask Her Majesty’s Government to think again and bring forward the second stage of leasehold reform in this Session as a matter of urgency. I request that the Minister clarifies the situation and treats these issues with the importance that they deserve. I commend Her Majesty’s Government and the Minister, the noble Lord, Lord Greenhalgh, on passing the ground rent Act in the last Session.</p>
    <p pid="a83.0/4">On the proposed renters reform Bill, I support the abolition of no-fault evictions by removing Section 21 of the Housing Act 1988, which has often been seen as unfair and contributes to tenants’ insecurity of tenure. However, I add three provisos. First, landlords should always be able to seek possession in the case of rent arrears. Most landlords own only one or two properties and are not Rachman-style slum landlords. They rely on rental income to pay the mortgage—if they have one—maintenance costs and service charges, and often to supplement increasingly inadequate state pensions. Secondly, many landlords are accidental landlords, or landlords for just a period of their lives. If they personally need to reoccupy their homes, they should be able to do so. The noble Lord, Lord Carrington, referred to some of these issues. Thirdly, fair rent reviews must be built into the system. Costs go up for landlords as well as tenants, and rents should at least be able to rise over time in line with the consumer price index or another appropriate measure.</p>
    <p pid="a83.0/5">It is regrettable that, in addition to a database for rogue landlords and property agents, Her Majesty’s Government are not legislating to regulate property management agents. Estate agents are legally regulated, so I see no reason why equally important property  management agents are not. The 2019 recommendations of the Regulation of Property Agents working group have been ignored. Property management agents tend to fall into three categories: those managed by right to manage companies that are professional and competent; those managed by RTM companies that are wholly unprofessional and incompetent; and professional property management companies whose sole purpose seems to be to act on behalf of the freeholder and burden leaseholders with excessive costs, including extortionate commissions and overly expensive works.</p>
    <p pid="a83.0/6">The second stage of leasehold reform is well overdue. Our feudal leasehold system is precisely that: feudal, outdated and unique to England and Wales. Abuses of the system have been well documented in this House and elsewhere. The Leasehold Knowledge Partnership and the leasehold and commonhold reform APPG—I am a member of the latter—have done much valuable work on the issues facing leaseholders, of whom there are some 4.6 million in the country.</p>
    <p pid="a83.0/7">I welcome the Law Commission’s papers on exercising the right to manage and on leasehold home ownership. For those wishing to extend the length of their leases to ensure long-term tenure and preserve value, the current system is an arbitrary nightmare. As a surveyor told me recently, freeholders think of a lease extension valuation figure and double it. Surveyors and valuers then receive commission based on how much they can negotiate the lease extension figure down from an initial valuation that has no relation to market value. Again, all parties benefit apart from the leaseholder.</p>
    <p pid="a83.0/8">Abolition of so-called “marriage value” would be welcome. The proposed online calculator would also be of benefit. At last, leaseholders will be aware of the potential cost before embarking on the exercise. Her Majesty’s Government should firmly reject the specious argument made by some hedge funds that leasehold reform will imperil their human rights as property owners. If the law has to be changed to nullify this argument, it should be. In short, I look forward to the Government pressing ahead as soon as possible with legislation in this area that will offer real hope to renters and leaseholders.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.84.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.84.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.85.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.85.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.88.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.88.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.90.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.90.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11a.93.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-05-11b.93.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

