<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="/home/twfy-live/parldata/scrapedxml/lordspages/daylord2022-03-11a.xml" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1663.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1663.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1663.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1663.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1663.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1663.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1666.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1666.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1667.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1667.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1668.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1668.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1669.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1669.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1671.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1671.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1672.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1672.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1673.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1673.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1674.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1674.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1676.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1676.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1677.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1677.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1683.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1683.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1683.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1683.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1683.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1683.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1684.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1684.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1684.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1684.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1684.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1684.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1687.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1687.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1688.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1688.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1688.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1688.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1690.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1690.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1690.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1690.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1691.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1691.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1692.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1692.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1694.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1694.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1696.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1696.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1696.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1696.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1696.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1696.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1697.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1697.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1698.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1698.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1698.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1698.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1702.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1702.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1707.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1707.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1708.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1708.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1708.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1708.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1708.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1708.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1708.2" speakername="Lord Lipsey" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/13645" colnum="1708" time="13:05:00" url="">
    <p pid="a1708.2/1">My Lords, to tell your Lordships the truth, I feel like an imposter. This report was shaped, inspired and given its passion by Lord Puttnam, the chairman of the committee, who I am delighted to see sitting on the steps of the Throne. I was merely one of the team of Peers who he charmed, argued and occasionally cajoled into unanimously endorsing his vision: trust in democracy resurrected by getting social media back on the leash. David’s high seriousness was of course combined with his impish sense of humour. He egged on his team—noble Lords and an incomparable secretariat led by Olivia Crabtree and Tim Stacey—to produce an irresistible report. We have lost him, and that fact highlights the extraordinary situation that it has taken nearly two years, or at least more than 18 months, from the time we produced our report to its being debated in this House—honestly.</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/2">However, Lord Puttnam and we should take comfort from the fact that the seeds we sowed have multiplied. To cite some: the Joint Committee on the Draft Online Safety Bill flowed directly from our work, and its report—unlike so many parliamentary reports—is being taken seriously by the Government. That is a continuing debate, but I predict it will have a much more satisfactory outcome than it would have done if our report had never existed. We had an impact on this House’s Communications and Digital Committee report of July 2021. That committee also produced a persuasive report on digital regulation, which makes real some of the Puttnam committee’s recommendations. The House of Commons Petitions Committee produced its valuable report on Tackling Online Abuse, which again picked up some of our themes.</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/3">Things that Puttnam said at the time which then seemed controversial now seem commonplace. As David said in his foreword,</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/4" class="indent">“our Report focuses on a different form of crisis, one with roots that extend far deeper, and are likely to last far longer than COVID-19. This is a virus that affects all of us in the UK—a pandemic of ‘misinformation’ and ‘disinformation’. If allowed to flourish these counterfeit truths will result in the collapse of public trust, and without trust democracy as we know it will simply decline into irrelevance.”</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/5">Let me dip briefly into the nourishing pot of proposals that Puttnam put forward. Among them are: a CMA full investigation into online platforms’ control over digital advertising—there was a giant step that way in the CMA’s announcement yesterday. There is also holding platforms to account for content they recommend to large audiences, coupled with Ofcom sanctions against platforms that fail to adhere to their duty of care; better co-ordination of regulators; transparency, especially transparency over the genie in the box, algorithms; using technology to engage people for democratic purposes; a large-scale programme of evaluation of digital media literacy initiatives, perhaps focusing, as the committee did, on the extraordinary efforts made by Estonia as part of its efforts to keep Russian misinformation at bay—we know now that not a moment of that has been wasted; and a major review of the implications of platform design for users, producing a code of practice on design transparency. I will not go on, because all noble Lords will have read the report or, if they have not, they will have read the excellent Library briefing, but a cornucopia of goodies is hidden within the report.</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/6">Not all our proposals were addressed to the Government. One, for example, was addressed to Parliament, recommending it set up a Joint Committee on online safety. As I have said, that happened—to remarkable effect. The CMA and Ofcom also both reacted and have been pushing ahead.</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/7">What of those recommendations addressed to the Government? Perhaps one should not expect the Government’s response to the report, which they published in—gulp—September 2020, to match the positive tone of our report. We know you do not get many positive tones in government responses. There are a few areas where progress is being made: imprints on digital political advertising, for example, and, at long last, the beginning of a joined-up approach in government to digital literacy. However, overall, there is something rather depressing about the response. Our committee had high ambitions. The Government have low ambitions—tarnished, moreover, by putting the partisan before the health of the polity in the Elections Bill that we debated only yesterday.</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/8">By serendipity, we were discussing electoral law in the previous debate. We were not the only people advocating reform: the Law Commission has a set of proposals. Yet the Government chose to prioritise this partisan Elections Bill—a shocking aberration—over making the change the Law Commission wanted.</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/9">We wanted proper declarations of spending by everyone in elections, not just political parties. The Government says that we must take care not to “overburden campaigners”. We proposed more powers for the Electoral Commission. The Elections Bill which the House debated emasculates the commission. We asked for a Bill based on the Law Commission’s recommendations, and we wanted it in place before the next general election. There is no sign of it yet; it remains in the long grass. The Government need to get their priorities straight where electoral law is concerned if they are to retain the confidence of voters. We were an all-party committee recommending changes to sustain  democracy. I fear that, too often, they seem a partisan Government, recommending changes to bend democracy their way.</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/10">These debates are not over: far from it. Much of what we raised is being taken forward, as I said —at least in debate if not always in legislative action. I must also say that the tone of debate has improved radically. Nobody now defends the exploitation of children by pornographers—as the noble Baroness, Lady Kidron, has frequently pointed out. The Government are actually doing something about it by announcing measures to ensure that age verification is taken seriously. Having said some harsh things about the Government, I cannot tell your Lordships how thrilled I—and, I am sure, the noble Baroness, Lady Kidron—was to find that they were taking some action there. I expect that, like me, she will not be totally satisfied. It is also important that the big tech companies themselves are finally starting to take their critics seriously—that is what a febrile share price does under capitalism—and they are now making not just public affairs but genuine efforts to start to get together their solidate.</p>
    <p pid="a1708.2/11">I look forward to the debate and to the Minister’s reply. I have been long enough—may be too long—in politics to have learned how often the short term trumps the long term, how a few votes snatched today can seem more attractive than a healthier democracy tomorrow. In this report, we tried to create a counterweight: an appeal, if you like, to idealism to defeat a widespread and corrosive cynicism. Even today, what we said is a cry worth listening to for those who still believe in progress and democracy, and all of us believe in those two things more strongly as a result of the horrifying events in Ukraine. The report is Lord Puttnam’s legacy and let us hope that it will be his words that shape our future.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1710.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1710.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1712.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1712.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1713.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1713.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1714.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1714.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1716.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1716.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1717.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1717.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1718.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1718.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1720.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1720.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1721.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1721.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1722.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1722.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1724.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1724.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1727.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1727.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1729.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1729.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11a.1734.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2022-03-11b.1734.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

