<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="/home/twfy-live/parldata/scrapedxml/lordspages/daylord2016-05-19a.xml" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.27.8" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.27.8" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.28.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.28.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.28.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.28.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.28.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.28.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.28.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.28.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.28.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.28.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.28.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.28.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.28.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.28.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.32.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.32.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.36.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.36.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.39.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.39.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.41.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.41.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.43.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.43.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.45.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.45.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.47.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.47.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.49.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.49.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.52.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.52.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.54.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.54.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.57.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.57.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.59.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.59.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.59.0" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10345" speakername="Lord Kirkwood of Kirkhope" colnum="59" time="13:03:00" url="">
    <p pid="a59.0/1">My Lords, it is a real pleasure to follow the noble Lord, Lord Murphy of Torfaen, and I absolutely concur with the approach he has taken in directing the Government’s attention to the fact that the landscape constitutionally has changed across and throughout the United Kingdom. It affects not only devolution and some of the important policy areas he mentioned such as higher education, but all the decentralisation measures which both in principle and philosophically are probably right to contemplate. That is because if anything, the United Kingdom is an over-centralised state. We must be careful about “powerhouses”, private prisons and private schools, all of which individually and on a freestanding basis might make sense, but do not necessarily all fit together. The House should be mindful of that during the rest of this year, as we consider the content of the Queen’s Speech. The Government therefore have a responsibility to pay attention to the speech of the noble Lord, Lord Murphy.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/2">The Government should also make it clear that they will not totally ignore local authorities. Local government is part of the constitutional warp and weft of all parts of the United Kingdom, and there is a sense that things are being done over the heads of duly elected members of local authorities. We on these Benches pay a lot more than lip service to the crucial work that councillors do for their communities. I am therefore pleased to support the main contention set out in the noble Lord’s speech.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/3">This Queen’s Speech has no real edge to it. I have been reading Queen’s Speeches for many years, and in my judgment this one is limited in scope and is a rehash of previous plans. I hope that the Minister, in her reply—it is a tough task to respond to a debate of this range and depth; I would not have her job but I am sure she will make a fine fist of it—will take note of the three powerful speeches made from our Front Bench. They were all, in their different ways about investment and pressures in the system—whether in the health service, the business world or our cultural and media spheres—and they were all mindful of the ever-present austerity as we go through the rest of this Parliament. A worry that we all share on these Benches is that people think the economy is better, the job has been done, the Chancellor is going to get his big prize of a balanced budget some time soon and everything is going to be fine. That is not the reality in the country, and the House needs to bear that in mind when it considers the detail of the legislative programme that has been laid before it.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/4">Infrastructure will be a crucial issue for the country over the next couple of years. There may not be any primary legislation to deal with it, but we need to note  that infrastructure is not just about roads and railways; it is also about broadband. I would like housing and the capital work necessary to deal with climate change issues to be adequately considered as part of the infrastructure plan. The noble Lord, Lord Adonis, has been listening intently to the debate until just now. We are lucky that the noble Lord is playing such a key role for the Government. I applaud that because he is an excellent person, and I hope the Government will take proper account of anything he says.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/5">At the same time, I hope the Government are realistic about what they can do. There are many examples of claims and counter-claims being made in press releases that the public do not actually believe any more. Government departments—or perhaps spads—always overclaim and underdeliver when it should be the other way around. I am sure that the Minister knows that, because she has a lot of experience in business. I hope she can help on that issue.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/6">I want to say a word of support for the comments of the right reverend Prelate the Bishop of Durham and the noble Earl, Lord Listowel. We have often been in the same camp during many campaigns over the months and years. The right reverend Prelate was absolutely right to say that austerity is getting worse because of the reductions in the social security budget, which are creating adversity for many low-income families. As he rightly said, universal credit is being stripped out. I support everything he said, and I will work shoulder to shoulder with him to make sure that the Government take account of these issues.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/7">A lot of statistics fly around, and people talk about a few billions here and a few billions there, but to reinforce the point made by the right reverend Prelate, as recently as this Monday the Office for National Statistics published some information about persistent poverty rates in the United Kingdom and the European Union. In 2014, 6.5% of the UK population was in persistent poverty, equivalent to approximately 3.9 million people. Colleagues will remember that persistent poverty is defined as experiencing relative low income in the current year and in at least two out of the three preceding years. That is a serious situation for a country such as ours. Interestingly, the ONS figures also point out that persistent poverty bears down unduly on women and single-person households. We do not do that well in comparison with our European sister countries on the issue of experiencing poverty at least once in the past three or four years. We have work to do.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/8">Austerity is still with us. That will play into the Government’s life chances strategy, which the right reverend Prelate also mentioned. I am certainly prepared to work with this strategy. The troubled families issues are important and the strategy is effective, but mentoring and early years assistance cannot put food on the table and pay rent. If people in low-income households cannot put food on the table and pay rent, they are under stress, which causes heartache and marriage breakdown. I know that that is not in the Government’s long-term interests or plans.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/9">Finally, the disability employment gap, which I think the right reverend Prelate also mentioned, is a key measure for the rest of the Parliament. I am sure that that view is shared across the House. It is a very ambitious target but no reference is made to it in the  Queen’s Speech. There is the White Paper, expected later in the summer, which some of us will look at very carefully. Innovation and sensitivity will be required, and we will need to avoid the kind of mistakes we made in reassessing the PIP 50-metre test to 20 metres, for example. But even if the new Secretary of State for Work and Pensions uses the time between now and the summer to come up with a plan to address that point, it can possibly be done without extra investment. We certainly wait with anticipation to see what he comes up with in the summer. I hope that that will lead to legislation—the “other measures” that the noble Lord, Lord Fowler, referred to.</p>
    <p pid="a59.0/10">The Speech is not mindful enough of the continuing pressure on low-income families and deprived and persistent poverty groups. In the coming weeks and months, the House would do well to recognise that in considering the detail of the Bills in the Queen’s Speech.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.61.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.61.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.63.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.63.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.65.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.65.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.67.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.67.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.69.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.69.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.70.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.70.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.73.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.73.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.74.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.74.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.76.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.76.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.78.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.78.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.80.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.80.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.82.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.82.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.84.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.84.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.86.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.86.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.88.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.88.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.91.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.91.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.92.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.92.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.94.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.94.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.97.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.97.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.98.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.98.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.99.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.99.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.101.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.101.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.103.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.103.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.105.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.105.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.106.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.106.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.108.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.108.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.111.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.111.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.113.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.113.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.115.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.115.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.117.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.117.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19a.121.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2016-05-19b.121.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

